<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Maister Bezaes houshold prayers translated out of French into English.</title>
            <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 186 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2023.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1181</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21541070</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21541070</idno>
            <idno type="VID">24771</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 24771)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1720:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Maister Bezaes houshold prayers translated out of French into English.</title>
                  <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[368] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By V.S. for Iohn Barnes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title and text within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸(-A1,A8) B-P¹² Q¹⁰.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
            <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
         </gap>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:24771:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24771:1"/>
            <head>To the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>and moſt</hi> vertuous, Miſtriſſe <hi>Francis Smith.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doe heere offer vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue (which dooth yet make you more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy then the worth of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:2"/>your moſt Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble birth) theſe vn-Frenched Prayers, which the religious zeale of that reuerend man, Beza of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua, hath in his priuate Exerciſes povvred out vnto GOD. To commend their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie vnto you, by my iudgement, were to commend them to little; and therefore,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:2"/>let your owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (as it can beſt) conceiue their worth; and your godly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, in making vſe of them, ſupplie whatſoeuer want of grace is come vnto them, by my chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theyr language, in the weight and life which your vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſhal giue them. To none could they
<pb facs="tcp:24771:3"/>be addreſſed by mee, ſo fitly, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of your vertue (prone to affect ſuch religious exerciſes) and for the reſpect &amp; ſeruice I owe your woorthie Husband, (whoſe fauour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes me doth iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly challenge a moſt grateful acknowlege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;) And therfore if you will be pleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:24771:3"/>graciouſly to receiue theſe Prayers at my hands, you ſhall adde to their number this one, That God (to whom they are ſent) will, both heere on Earth, &amp; in Heauen, bleſſe you with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable felicity.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>At your commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment moſt humbly I. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:24771:4"/>
            <head>A Table of the Praiers contained in this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 A prayer vppon the Lordes prayer.</item>
               <item>2 A prayer vppon the Beliefe.</item>
               <item>3 A prayer vppon the tenne Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</item>
               <item>4 A prayer to one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God in Trinitie of perſons.</item>
               <item>5 A prayer to knowe God in Ieſus Chriſt.</item>
               <item>6 A prayer for obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:24771:4"/>of the gift of the Holyghoſt.</item>
               <item>7 A prayer to God for the light of his word.</item>
               <item>8 A prayer that wee may not depart from the holy Church.</item>
               <item>9 A prayer to obtaine the efficacie of holie Baptiſme.</item>
               <item>10 A prayer for the Communion of the holie Euchariſt.</item>
               <item>11 A prayer to giue thanks after the Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munion.</item>
               <item>12 A praier to obtaine the gift of Faith.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:5"/>
               <item>13 A prayer to obtaine the vertue of Hope.</item>
               <item>14 A prayer to obtaine the virtue of Charitie.</item>
               <item>15 A praier for the wel vſing of afflictions.</item>
               <item>16 A praier to obtaine the virtue of patience</item>
               <item>17 A praier for the wel vſing of mans life.</item>
               <item>18 A praier vpon tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall death.</item>
               <item>19 A prayer vpon hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly life.</item>
               <item>20 A prayer vppon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death.</item>
               <item>21 A morning prayer.</item>
               <item>22 A prayer among a
<pb facs="tcp:24771:5"/>Family.</item>
               <item>23 A Prayer beefore meate.</item>
               <item>24 A Prayer to giue thanks after meate.</item>
               <item>25 An euening praier among a family.</item>
               <item>26 A Prayer for him that ſuffreth much by ſickeneſſe.</item>
               <item>27 A prayer in the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation of the ſicke.</item>
               <item>28 A prayer for him that feeleth him ſelfe to be neere death.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>The end of the Table.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:24771:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24771:6"/>
            <head>To al Chriſtians, zealous in holy Prayers.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 21.</bibl>
                  <p>The Kingdome of God is at hand, watch therfore, praying at all times.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F wee are indued with the true knowlege of our estate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as alſo, the efficacie of holy prayers, wee ſhoulde not neede to be aduertiſed often, to preſent our ſelues before God, to offer vnto him our vowes, and to beſeech his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue, or dilection, for
<pb facs="tcp:24771:7"/>guiding vs, by his good ſpirit, vnto the light of his trueth, to encreaſe in our heartes, faith, loue, conſtancie, humilitie, and other his heauenly giftes, to forgiue vs our debts, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the corruptions of our nature, to clothe vs with his ſpirituall armour, againſt the aſſaults of the diuel, the world &amp; the fleſh, to prouide for our neceſſities, to preſerue vs from infinite dangers, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe vs round about: to be ſhort, to graunt vs his holie ſpirite, to guide the whole courſe of our life, to the glorie of his name, and the peace and ſaluation of our owne ſoules. For, he who hath not a feeling
<pb facs="tcp:24771:7"/>of the great want of all theſe graces, or bleſſings, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, the neceſſitie of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto God, for obtaining the ſame, knoweth not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but is ſenſleſſe and voyd of all feeling. By prayer wee bleſſe God for his goodneſſe, power, wiſedome, iustice, and mercy towardes vs: becauſe of our prayers, he bleſſeth vs, in doing vs good, and distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting his benefites amongest vs: it is vnto vs, as the ſoule of our ſoules: for that prayer quickeneth our affections, and lifteth vppe our heartes vnto heauen; which otherwiſe wold be dead in ſinnes and trespaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by following the vanities
<pb facs="tcp:24771:8"/>of this wicked world. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is as it were the key which openeth vnto vs the treaſury of our heauenly Father, as faith is the hand, laying holde vpon thoſe ſure and perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent poſſeſſions of eternall life, the deſire whereof, ſhould cauſe vs continually to pray vnto, and feruently to loue God. Prayer maketh, that in the miſeries of this life, wee comfort our ſelues, by looking for the benefites of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. Prayer refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth vs through the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his gracious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which confirme vs in the ſame, and of the bleſſings al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready receiued at his hands,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:8"/>which moue vs in our neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to hope for the like, and wait for it, with al patience. It augmenteth in vs, a deſire to be conioyned with him, throgh our Lorde Ieſus Christ, in whome all our good doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſist. It cheereth vs in thoſe workes, which the holy ghost worketh in vs, &amp; by vs, yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſweet ſmell to our ſouls, and is moreouer vnto vs, as a ſtrong Tower, and most aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fortreſſe, against all that might astoniſh vs, in this our earthly habitation: yea which is more, prayer doth ſomtimes ſtand vs inſteede, to obtaine of Almighty God, moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent testimonies of his glorie,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:9"/>in matters ſupernaturall, which our reaſon ſhould iudge impoſſible, as it befell vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> praying for the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of the Iſraelites, against the Amalekites: to <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> when at his praier, the courſe of the Sunne was ſtayed: to <hi>Elias,</hi> bringing fire down from heauen, and to <hi>Ezechias</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to helth after ſentence given of his death: not that wee ſhould ſimply attribute ſo great and profitable effects to the woorke of prayer: but to the goodneſſe, loue, power, and counſell of God, who worketh ſo, and by ſuch meanes as hee pleaſeth in his creatures: and of his free mercie, crowneth
<pb facs="tcp:24771:9"/>the prayers of his elect with rewardes, and with grace for grace. Theſe therefore are the fruits and benefites we are to looke for from our good god and father, when repoſing our ſelues vpon his loue in Chriſt, and with humble and penitent hearts, wee doe proſtrate our ſelues before his face, to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie his name, crauing his mercie, and beſeeching him to bleſſe vs, teach and guide vs as his children, to beleeue his word, euen as he whom we cal vpon, doth deſire our good, bicauſe he loueth vs, may giue vnto vs that we aske, becauſe he is almighty: and is willing to heare vs, for his Sonnes
<pb facs="tcp:24771:10"/>ſake, becauſe hee hath ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. But it is alſo moſt true, that acording to his wiſdome, he knoweth the time and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient meanes, to let vs ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enioy the efficacie of our praiers. Let vs perſeuer, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly asking thoſe things which are to his glorie, and hee will not faile to helpe vs in all our neceſſities. Wee are moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to note, that it is not the ſound of the lippes which the Lord requireth of vs, vnleſſe the ſame be alſo guided with the holy affections of the ſoule: for he harkneth rather to the heart than to the voyce, and giueth to vs openly that which he ſeeth vs in ſecret to deſire
<pb facs="tcp:24771:10"/>with our affections mortified in his ſight. Therefore wee muſt (praying carefully) lift vppe our heartes with a true zeale to GOD, baniſhing out all other thoughts, aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning Sathan with all his baites, opening our harts, that our Heauenly Father may thereinto infuſe and powre downe his bleſſings. Neyther ought our prayer to bee bare or naked, but conioyned with reading, and meditation of Gods holy worde, as alſo fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>But alas, if it bee moſt true, that in all our exerciſes of piety wee be neuer able to ſeperate our ſelues from our
<pb facs="tcp:24771:11"/>ſelues, but that our corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wil ſtil euidently appeare, it is ſure, the ſame will eſpecially befall vs, when wee prepare our ſelues to pray vnto God, and frame our petitions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will: for beſides that the diuel doth at al times lie in waite, to ſeduce vs, ſo doeth hee, eſpecially, at ſuch times, ſeeke to creepe into our minds, to diuert our thoughts elſewhere, that they may bee polluted with many blemiſhes: notwithſtanding, that they of themſelues, ſufficiently goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray: yea our vanitie, imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and coldneſſe, doeth many wayes bewray it ſelfe, that we may well ſay, in one
<pb facs="tcp:24771:11"/>word: no man prayeth right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but he, whoſe mouth and minde Chriſt doth direct with his ſpirit. And therefore hath he deliuered vnto vs, a ſacred forme, for all holy prayers, in that prayer which is vſually termed, <hi>The Lords Prayer,</hi> wherein, hee hath ſet downe, the perfect rule, whereby, we may rightly forme our petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and keepe them within their bounds: that is, <hi>the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, &amp; our ſaluation.</hi> And this are wee dilligently to note, as being aſſured, that ſo we ſhall be heard, albeit our frailty do hinder vs, from pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing with that zeale, feeling, and feruency of faith, which
<pb facs="tcp:24771:12"/>true prayer doth require. Let vs winne from our ſelues ſo much as wee may, calling to minde, for our comfort, that we do offer our prayers, to the father, in the name of his wel-beloued ſonne, and by his own mouth, couered with his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe: who therefore will accept of them, according to his promiſe, but withall, let vs alſo remember, that ſuch, who vſe many times to ſay, <hi>O Lord help vs,</hi> do not, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, thereby obtaine ſaluation: but they, who doe his will, and to that end, doth he command vs, that we haue his word dwelling peaceably in our hearts, that we may be
<pb facs="tcp:24771:12"/>ready to performe euery good worke.</p>
            <p>Theſe things, therefore, being by God conioyned vnto prayer, let vs take great heed, that wee ſeperate them not, conſidering, that by the ſame, we conuerſe with our father which is in heauen, and ſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, the fulneſſe of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings: for whenſoeuer we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our eyes, or our eares, to thoſe things, which he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto vs, in the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, hee ſpeaketh vnto vs, and calling vpon his name, we ſpeake vnto him.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, in aſmuch as, naturally wee are but little inclined, or rather vtterly
<pb facs="tcp:24771:13"/>careleſſe, of theſe ſpirituall exerciſes, it will not be amiſſe, if we reſtraine our ſelues, to praier, at certaine houres of the day: not for ſuperſtition, but to withſtand our ſlouth, ſlackeneſſe, and other worldly matters, which otherwiſe might induce vs, to ouerſlippe diuerſe dayes, without any practiſe of this duetie. <hi>Dauid</hi> bearing vppon his ſhoulders the burden of a great King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, prayed, morning, at noone, and at night: yea ſeauen times a day, did he ſing prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to God, day and night me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating in his Lawe. Nowe therefore (gentle Readers) feeling my ſelf toward the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining
<pb facs="tcp:24771:13"/>euening of my dayes, with a taſte of ſo many ſolide, and permanent ioyes, as are daily to be found in prayer: &amp; withall, being inflamed with a deſire, to finiſh the reſt of my courſe, in this ſweete labour, which I finde to be accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, with ſo large a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, I haue here formed for my ſelfe, and for any other, that liſt to reade it, this ſmall mannell, of holy, ſhort, and familiar prayers, grounded vpon the texts of ſcriptures, ſuch as are indeed, to inſtruct, comfort, and make vs perfect, in faith, loue, conſtancy, and to be ſhort, in all chriſtian life. Be of good cheere then, (all
<pb facs="tcp:24771:14"/>godly ſoules) and let vs v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite all our petitions, in this ſo deuoute, and profitable an exerciſe, of all true faithfull people. Let vs pray, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate, if not inceſſantly, yet at the leaſt, dayly at certaine ſet houres, and as often as wee may, as well in the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as in our families, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and euening amongſt our houſhold, as alſo in our ſecret chambers. Thus ſhall wee with our lippes, vpon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars of our hearts, offer vp, many acceptable ſacrifices of ſweete ſauor before his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, whereof, the benefite will redound to our ſelues, in that God will bleſſe vs, in our
<pb facs="tcp:24771:14"/>vocations, workes, and labors. Oh, how happy ſhall theſe men then be, whom the Lord ſhall finde thus watching, and praying! for they ſhall depart vnto him in peace, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of his glory; which grace, God graunt vnto vs all. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:24771:15"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Royal seal</figDesc>
                  <head>E R</head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:24771:15"/>
            <head>Holie Prayers of a faithfull Soule.</head>
            <head type="sub">For the Conſolation and Perfection of a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian life.</head>
            <div n="1" type="prayer">
               <head>The firſt Prayer, Vpon the Lords Prayer.</head>
               <p>When you pray, vſe no vaine repetitions, as the Heathen: for they thinke to be heard for their much babbling. Be yee not like them therefore: for your
<pb facs="tcp:24771:16"/>Father knoweth whereof yee haue neede before yee aske of him. After this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner therefore pray yee:</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>Mat. <hi>6.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Our Father which arte in Heauen:</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, the knowledge of whome is life, whome to ſerue, is to raigne, and vnto whom to pray, is the ioy and peace of the ſoule, wee cannot knowe thee, but in thine owne image Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb facs="tcp:24771:16"/>Chriſt, and that by the operation of thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: neither ſerue thee, except wee follow thy word: neither call vpon thee, but in the name of the ſame Chriſt, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that forme, which himſelf hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed vs. Thus euerie faithfull creature ſayeth vnto thee. <hi>Our Father, giue vnto vs, forgiue vs.</hi> For thus hath thy ſonne, the head of that vnion, which is among al chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, commanded, that our prayers ſhould bee
<pb facs="tcp:24771:17"/>common for al thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; as being all one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which thou gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt by one onely ſpirite: and foraſmuch as our being dependeth vppon thee onely, and being in our birth corrupted by ſinne, thou makeſt vs to be renewed vnto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, through the ſame eternal word, wher by thou haſt created vs, we doe rightly cal thee, euen by a double right, <hi>Our Father.</hi> A happie, and louing beginning of prayer, wherin the new
<pb facs="tcp:24771:17"/>man, reconciled vnto thee, in Ieſus Chriſt, thus ſpeaketh to thee his father: I do beleeue that I am of the number of thy children, through thy mercy, which it hath pleaſed thee to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe me; and therfore (O my God) I cannot ſee doubt hereof, but that thou doſt louingly heare me, and art inclined to helpe me, and to relieue me in all my neceſſities, conſidering thou arte in heauen, euen according as being in al places, thou
<pb facs="tcp:24771:18"/>art as it were in no place, for thou art wholie an infinite ſpirite, and inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible light, whoſe name is <hi>(I am)</hi> namelie of a ſole, true eſſence, eternall, immutable and incomprehenſible, and from whom, all nature, whether celeſtiall, or ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall, doeth, through grace, borrowe his eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and ſubſiſtence. Thus arte thou aboue, in ſuch wiſe, that being out of euery place, thou art aboue all this great vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall world, in the ſeate
<pb facs="tcp:24771:18"/>of thine own glory, from whence, thou doeſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace both heauen and earth, and with thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, ſuſtaine them. As alſo, in ſome ſorte thou art aboue al things, becauſe they doe all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, and beare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vppon thee, who likewiſe, doſt by thy ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitie pierce into them, more neerly vnto euery creature then the ſame is to it ſelfe. Howbeit, thou art in heauen, ſo far forth, as that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite workes of thy
<pb facs="tcp:24771:19"/>hands, do the better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare therein. And thou doeſt in an eſpeciall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner inhabite the high heauen: for there doeth thy Maieſtie ſhine with open countenaunce: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, thou art with thy gracious preſence in the ſoules of the righteous, which do harbour thee as a Father in their heartes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>[Hallowed be thy name.]</head>
                  <p>FOr, O Lord, ſith thou art my father, reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:24771:19"/>requireth, that aboue all things, I ſhould deſire thy honour. But euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly, for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, thy name is holy, &amp; the glory therof infinit. My praier then bringeth nothing to thy greatnes and excellencies: but yet I may heere deſire, that thy name, both of it ſelf, and by it ſelfe, moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, may be ſanctified, and exalted in me, and in all men, and in all places: whereby my ſelfe do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo obtaine that holines, which is conuenient for
<pb facs="tcp:24771:20"/>the true childe of ſuch a father, vnto whome all vncleaneneſſe is diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>[Thy kingdome come.]</head>
                  <p>But who can impeach thy Kingdome, O e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall God, who haſt created al things, for thy ſeruice? Thou raigneſt ouer al; for the heauen is thy throne, and the earth thy foote-ſtoole: Yet I beſeech thee, be vnto me, as a father in mercy, not as a Iudge in thy iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice:
<pb facs="tcp:24771:20"/>thou raigneſt in thy worde, which thou haſt reuealed, and inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and I beſeech thee, euen for thy glory ſake, that this thy booke of life, may bee opened to all people, that thereby all nations may worſhip thee: thou raigneſt in thy Church, and I pray, that the number of thy elect may be ſhortly ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. Thy kingdome is thy grace, and I beſeech thee to make mee as ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable thereof, as thou art liberall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:24771:21"/>
                  <head>[Thy wil be done in earth as it is in heauen.</head>
                  <p>MY will, O Lord, is altogether peruers and depraued, except it bee formed by thine, wherin reſteth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth all my good: cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in me this holy will, and giue mee grace to fulfil it, in al my thoghts &amp; workes: (for what can I haue, but what thou giueſt mee?) To the end that in obedience of faith, I may doe that
<pb facs="tcp:24771:21"/>which ſhall bee accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in thy ſight, euen as the Angells in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen do obey thy voyce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>[Giue vs this day our dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie bread.</head>
                  <p>FOR Chriſt our Lord and Doctour, hath ſo contriued the petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which we make vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, that in ſeeking firſt the glorie of thy name, hee will, that with al, we ſhould haue expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, of the riches of thy goodneſſe, in all
<pb facs="tcp:24771:22"/>things neceſſary for this life. Thus wilt thou (O merciful Father) recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with infinite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, euen our ſimple cogitations of the bright<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of thy glory, and crowne thy giftes in vs with grace for grace. We do therefore dayly craue our bread, and thou doſt alſo giue it vs, that is to ſay, euen all that is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for our maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance heere beneathe: yet doeſt thou preſent vs with one bread farre more excellent and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitabl,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:22"/>euen the bread of angels, and of the bleſſed ſpirits: giue mee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (O Lord) Ieſus Chriſt, God and man, that of him I may liue for euer, that my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding may bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned with his truth, and my heart kindled with the fire of his loue, that I periſh not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>And forgiue vs our treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes as we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:24771:23"/>
                  <p>OVr ſinnes as debts do bind vs to death (which is their rewarde) and to hell (which is their graue) they are as a ſtrong barre, to keepe vs from comming to thee (O moſt holy God) yea which is more, they are as a clowde that ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doweth thine eyes, from looking fauourably vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs. And therefore the moſt conuenient prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to prayer, is with an humble, and truely penitent heart, to feele
<pb facs="tcp:24771:23"/>and confeſſe our ſinnes: for ſo thou wilt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to grant vs remiſſion of the ſame, in the name of thy ſonne our Sauior, in imputing vnto vs his righteouſneſſe. Yet here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (O Lord) is thy free mercy very great, that thou alſo giueſt vs pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to pardon thoſe that doe offend vs, and by ſo dooing, to obtaine thy grace: for what offence can any man commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, (poore worms of the earth) conſidering that we do ſo often, and
<pb facs="tcp:24771:24"/>ſo grieuouſly offend (O King of glory) and in ſuch ſorte, that if euery creature ſhould arme it ſelf to hurt vs, yet would not the leaſt iniurie that we commit againſt thee be ſufficiently reuenged. Yet doſt thou vouchſafe thus to teſtifie thy infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite goodneſſe, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting as a ſweete ſacrifice, the oblation of our harts reconciled, and fully v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited with our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, like as contrarywiſe no part of a hateful and peruerſe heart can
<pb facs="tcp:24771:24"/>delight thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>And leade vs not into temptation, but deliuer vs from euill.</head>
                  <p>FOr, as through thy mercy, thou ſuffereſt not Satan (the author of all temptations) to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce thy children, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinne to ouercome them, ſo when thou wilt puniſh man in thy iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, they remaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of thy protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and vnder the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the diuell to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
<pb facs="tcp:24771:25"/>to his tyrany, and to liue in a reprobate ſence, hereof doe we therefore reape this ſingular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, that this great aduerſarie of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can doe nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, vnleſſe thou giue him leaue: and whereas ſometimes thou cauſeſt vs to be tempted, thou doeſt it as a father, to chaſtice vs for our tranſgreſſions, or to make vs more trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant and victorious in the triall, which it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee to make of our
<pb facs="tcp:24771:25"/>faith, and hope, for thy glory, and our owne good, or for the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our neighbours.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For thine is the kingdome, the power, and the glory, for euer and euer.</head>
                  <p>LIke as (O my God and father) I began my prayer, by the hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of thy name, ſo is it meete and iuſt that I ſhould end it, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of the ſame: as thy children, who boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their vowes, with
<pb facs="tcp:24771:26"/>the onely care of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour may aſſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to obtaine the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the ſame in the ſole perfection of thy glory. So be it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſecond Prayer,</hi> Vpon the Symbole or Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Beliefe.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:24771:26"/>
                  <head>I beleeue in God the Father Almightie: &amp;c.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>1. Cor. 15.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Before all things I haue deliuered vnto you, that which I haue receyued, namely that Christ died for our ſinnes, according to the ſcriptures, and that hee was buried, &amp; that he roſe againe the third day.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God gouernour of the whol world, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:27"/>and onely wiſe, for whoſe glory al things are. It hath pleaſed thee, according to the decree of thy vnſerchable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, that man, formed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy image, &amp; falling through miſtruſt and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſitie, ſhould, by faith, be reſtored to the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of his nature; &amp; as he ſought knowledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo ſtrayed from thee, and wandred out of thy kingdome, ſo he ſhould be revnited, and reduced into the
<pb facs="tcp:24771:27"/>path of ſaluation, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing thy onely word in the promiſed Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, bending the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his ſoule, to the knowledge of thee, in embracing the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the croſſe, which the world would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt folly. But becauſe we al are borne blind, &amp; corrupt in our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and wil, it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore followeth, that all the imaginations and thoughts of our hearts are at all times nothing but euill, our knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:24771:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>but vanitie, our learning but ignorance, our iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but errour, our vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue but pride, our wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome but folly, the viua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of our ſpirit but the inſtrument of ruine, our delight but filthineſſe, our faith but increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; our hope but fancie, our charitie but coldnes, to be briefe, our pietie but hipocriſie or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition; and our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe but couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or ambition. So (O Lorde) we of our ſelues are not capable, ſomuch
<pb facs="tcp:24771:28"/>as of any good thought, vntill thou that knoweſt how to drawe light out of darkeneſſe doeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to recreate'vs, and by thy ſpirit to ſhine in the firmament of our ſoules, to the end to frame vs to euery faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſpoſition, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and ſo to make vs beleeue in the goſpell of thy grace, and in the myſteries of our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I doe therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee (my God) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the'fficacy of thy vertue, to change in
<pb facs="tcp:24771:29"/>me all that I haue of my ſelfe, euen my rockie and ſtony heart, and to make it pliable, and flex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ible, vnto the voice of my Redeemer, who is come according to thy promiſe, to the end, that with a ful and liuely faith I may cleaue to his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall truth, for to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, according to the meaſure of the gift of thy grace, the ſumme and perfection of al ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall wiſedome, which is taught vs in the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the true faith and
<pb facs="tcp:24771:29"/>ſound principles of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Surely my ſoule is ouermuch enclined to incredulity and miſtruſt, neither is it any way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to pierce into theſe high and profound ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of pietie, where we haue a full declaration of all the figures, and propheſies of the Lawe, with a moſt pure and perfite doctrine of foure pointes, which are the end of all religion, and in regard whereof it is called Catholike. For we find thee there (thou
<pb facs="tcp:24771:30"/>only and true God) the Father, authour and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of all things by thy almightie power, goodneſſe, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Next is our Lord Ieſus Chriſt (thy word and eternall wiſedome) therein taught vnto vs, together with the holy hiſtory of our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thirdly, wee there find the Holy-ghoſt (the infinite vertue of thee the father, and of the ſonne) three perſons, of one ſole, and ſimple eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and in equality of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:30"/>glory. And finally there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is ſhewed vnto vs, the Church, with a deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe celeſtiall graces, which thou pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt vpon her, whereof the forgiueneſſe of ſins is the ſumme, and life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting the onely ſcope. Giue therefore vnto me (O merciful fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) of this thy ſpirit of reuelation, of grace, and of mercy; to the end that the brightneſſe and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration therof may make my ſoule capable of theſe great myſteries of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:31"/>thy Kingdome, ſo farre forth as may be expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for me to know, for the ſeruice of thy glory, and my owne ſaluation, that I may obtaine the onely true and ſound knowledge, whoſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect and end is the onely true, ſolide; &amp; ſoueraign good, both of men and angells, namely to know thee, to glorifie thee, and him whome thou haſt ſent, the Sauiour of the worlde. So that with my hart I do belieue before thee, and before al men,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:31"/>I do with my words and workes, confeſſe this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable meſſage of the Meſſias come, borne in the Cittie of DAVID, which is CHRIST the lord God, manifeſted in the fleſh, iuſtified in the ſpirit, ſeene of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles, preached to the Gentiles, beleeued by the elect, and exalted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to glory, for our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, holineſſe, and glorification: And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo (O Almightie Lord) print in my heart the feeling &amp; knowlege
<pb facs="tcp:24771:32"/>of this thy vnſpeakable goodneſſe and loue, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended vnto vs miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinners, in that thou haſt giuen vnto vs in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, thy only Sonne, ſauing vs by the onely merits of his death, to the end, that as the efficacie of thy loue hath redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto mee wretched creature, ſo I may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſufficiently meditate vppon thy great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, inceſſantly yeelde thankes vnto thee, and feele thy eternall conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, vntil that I depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb facs="tcp:24771:32"/>in peace towardes thee my Father, which art in Heauen, may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine full knowledge of thoſe things that thou haſt giuen me to belieue, and in the perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the ſame, the ſoueraigne good of Angells and Saints. So be it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>The third Praier.</hi> Vpon the Decalogue, or ten Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:33"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>[God ſpake all theſe words, ſaying, Heare O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael: I am the Lord thy god, that hath brought thee out of the land of Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage: Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods before me, &amp;c.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Exod. 20.]</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord GOD Almightie, the Author of all righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and perfection of life; Yea euen thou that arte eſſentially Iuſtice, perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb facs="tcp:24771:33"/>and life. I doe tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know, that man crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted righteous &amp; perfect, and by cleauing to thee, bleſſed (but free and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table) hath, through ſin, turned from thee, plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging himſelfe headlong into the ſinke of vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, imperfection and death. The which hath depriued him of all power to obey the Law, and conſequently bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued him of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of eternall bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And albeit of eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall grace thou dooſt
<pb facs="tcp:24771:34"/>call vs, by the Goſpel, to the free righteouſnes of Chriſt, to the end, that beleeuing in him, wee might confeſſe him, for the obtayning of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Yet are we neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſo much inclined to diſtruſt, corruption, and diſorder, that hardly we are entred into the waie of his vocation, but we retyre immediatly, ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of that courſe which might purchaſe vnto vs the prize; and ſo through our workes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie our faith, and our
<pb facs="tcp:24771:34"/>profeſſion. Now as the firſt &amp; principal manner of thy honour (O one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true GOD) conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in beleeuing, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing our whole confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in thee alone: ſo the ſecond and inſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from true faith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in obedience to thy holy and good will. For we muſt be doers of that which thy holie worde teacheth vs, and not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers only, deceiuing our ſelues. Thou haſt cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and adopted vs to be thy Children: but it is
<pb facs="tcp:24771:35"/>vpon this condition, that wee ſhould be reformed to the Image of Ieſus Chriſt, the firſt borne, &amp; inheritour of all things. Thou haſt choſen vs to be his Temple: now his habitation cannot be but holy: for thy ſpirit dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth therein. Thou haſt redeemed vs with the price of his blood, and that to the ende thou maiſt bee glorified, both in our bodies and ſoules. Thou haſt freed vs from ſinne, euen to the ende we might be ſeruants to
<pb facs="tcp:24771:35"/>righteouſnes. Thou haſt giuen vs the Sauiour of the World, to be our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification: but to the end alſo that we poſſeſſe him in ſanctification. Thou wouldeſt that he ſhould die for all men, euen to make him liue in thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and they in him. And this is the reaſon wherfore the inſtitution of our faith, together with the ſpirituall conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations that ſupport the ſame, is accompanied with the ten precepts of thy law, the certaine and
<pb facs="tcp:24771:36"/>aſſured meanes to honor and ſerue thee, in liuing religiouſly to thy glory, &amp; vprightly to the profit of our neighbours. For albeit in the Goſpel wee be free from the rigor &amp; puniſhment of the Law, yet neuertheles, the rule of pietie and holie life contained in the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, abideth with vs, as a perpetuall patterne, whereby to frame our temporall courſe of life. And accordingly we do alſo conſider of it in two partes, according as it
<pb facs="tcp:24771:36"/>pleaſed thee, O Lord, to write it with thy finger, and to deliuer it vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> in two tables of ſtone, for thy people, whereof the firſt contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth foure Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of our duetie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes thee, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, ſixe, of that which wee owe to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors: Alſo the ſumme &amp; fulfilling of all theſe holy precepts importeth that wee loue thee, (O onely true GOD) with our whole heart, ſoule, and thought, and then all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:24771:37"/>men, (eſpecially the houſhold of faith) as our ſelues. But O Lord, ſuch is the weakeneſſe of all fleſh, that there is no man able to attain to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of thy Law: and yet thou willeſt, that here in, thy children ſhoulde comfort themſelues, that there is left vnto them, ſome meaſure to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach thervnto, and ſo to bee acceptable vnto thee; namely when with their whole ſtrength, preuented by thy grace, they ſtudie to attaine the
<pb facs="tcp:24771:37"/>end of thy word, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; going forward by the ſteps thereof, &amp; ſtill with ſighing for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities. For al the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full may ſo belieue, that with thee their Father there is mercy for them, in thy welbeloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. I beſeech thee therfore, O my God, to caſt vpon me, the eye of thy clemencie, and goodnes, therby throgh th'effects of thy ſpirit, to reſtore in my ſoule, the breaches of ſinne, to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate my vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:38"/>and to poſſeſſe my hart with the loue of thy truth, to the end that in all knowledge and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of faith, I may conſtantly walke in the paths of thy lawe; ſo that I may worſhip, ſcare, &amp; loue thee, as the Lord, to whome I wholy owe my ſelfe: for thou haſt created mee, and which is more, redeemed mee from eternall death, whence I do alſo learne to loue all men in thee, &amp; for thy ſake, becauſe they beare thy image, ſo that
<pb facs="tcp:24771:38"/>perſeuering thus in the duty of my vocation, I may ſo much the rather feele thy peace in my conſcience, and thy bleſſing vppon all the workes of my hands; that filled with dayes, I leaue my life, to enioy reſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="prayer">
               <head>The fourth praier. To one only God in Trinitie of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:39"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>God in the beginning created Heauen and earth, <hi>The word</hi> was with god, and this word was God: And the ſpirit of GOD mooued vpon the waters.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Gen. 1. Iohn. 1.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall, true, and only God in three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, coequall &amp; almightie, of one ſole, and ſimple eſſence, inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and infinite. The Father, the word and the holy Ghoſt, who being
<pb facs="tcp:24771:39"/>the ſoueraign good, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to thy ſelfe, nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding no newe matter, wouldeſt not for euer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy thy glorie alone, but according to thy vnmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable &amp; altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, reueale thy ſelfe at thy good pleaſure, in foure workes altogether diuine &amp; ſingular. (The creation of the world, &amp; of all nature: the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of mankinde: the building thy church, &amp; thy graces the ſame:) O Lord, who only art in
<pb facs="tcp:24771:40"/>trueth, permanent and ſtable; through whome euery thing is that is, in reſpect of whome, all is leſſe then nothing, who giuing by thy word beeing to that that was not at all, haſt, out of a confuſed, voyd, and dark ſubſtance, drawne light, beauty, and order, ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching forth the heauen as a vault or tent vnder the ſame, the earth, and the inhabitants thereof, who haſt made al things in number, weight, and meaſure: &amp; from whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:40"/>prouidence doeth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, the moderation and gouernement of all that is, whether it liueth, feeleth, or vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: O holy, thrice ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, admirable, and amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, who being righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, wouldeſt not ſuffer man, made after thy i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, to go vnpuniſhed when he had ſinned, and who, beeing mercifull, haſt not left him without grace: who, being good, haſt not neglected the leaſt of thy works, euen to the haire of a beaſt, the
<pb facs="tcp:24771:41"/>lighteſt fether of a fowl, and the leaſt flower or leafe of graſſe, in euery of theſe things, grauing certaine tokens of thy glory and maieſty by the harmonie &amp; agreement of al theſe ſmal creatures with the greateſt of the world: O Father, and moderator of all things! I beſeech thee, let thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall wiſedome reach to me euen through the light of thy ſpirit which ſeeth all things, which ſoundeth all thinges, which ſearcheth into all
<pb facs="tcp:24771:41"/>things, and which, with his preſence of grace, maketh his reſidence, in al peaceable cogitations, to lift them vp by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of his gifts, vnto the fanctuarie of thy ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celeſtiall pallace, there to make them ſee, heare, and worſhip, in ſpirit &amp; truth, the diuine maruels of thy Kingdome, &amp; the myſteries of the adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy elect. So that being thus taught by the moſt ſacred Oracles, I belieue in hart, and with vnderſtanding meditate
<pb facs="tcp:24771:42"/>vpon the true &amp; eternall exiſtence of thee (O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) borne of none, the firſt Soueraigne and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty cauſe of al things and eſpecially of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation throgh thy loue: Of thee (O Sonne) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally begotten by the Father, and by whom he hath made all his works, who art the principall cauſe, which giues vs life &amp; happines, according to the fulneſſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of thy loue, and of thee (O Holy Ghoſt) from al eternitie procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:24771:42"/>from the Father &amp; the Son, and by whome all creatures doe ſubſiſt, and ſaluation is commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated vnto vs; three perſons, of properties di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, yet not ſeperate; in vnitie of eſſence, and equalitie of glory: in thee one, and true God, not created, infinit, and almighty, &amp; the God of thy people. And that through this healthfull knowledge, I doe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſerue and call vpon thee only for euer, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out declining from thy
<pb facs="tcp:24771:43"/>word. Wherupon like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, through a ſtedfaſt faith in thy promiſes, depending vppon an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured hope, and true loue, I doe more and more draw vpon my ſelf the ſauour of thy holie bleſſings: to the end that as the Angels aboue doe praiſe thee, the powers of heauen do bleſſe thee, &amp; all the ſpiritual armies do magnifie thee, I like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe may heere belowe haue this felicitie, to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh my courſe in ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy praiſes, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:24771:43"/>leauing this terreſtriall life, to ioyne my ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to the celeſtial, with thoſe bleſſed ſpirits in the ful contemplation of thy face, to ſing with them without ende this ſong of perfect ioy (Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be to the Father that hath created vs; Glorie bee to thee Sonne that hath redeemed vs; Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be to the Holy-Ghoſt that hath ſanctified vs; Glorie bee to the moſt high Trinitie, one onely God and Lord, whoſe kingdome is euerlaſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:44"/>
               <head>The fift Prayer, For the obtaining of the knowledge of God in Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>The word was made fleſh, and dwelled among vs, full of grace and truth, the Image of the inuiſible God, which is Christ the Lord; who by himſelfe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing purged our ſinnes, ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the right hand of the Maiesty: in the higheſt places.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ioh. 1. Col. 1. Lu. 2 Heb. 1.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:44"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> GOD and Father of our Lord CHRIST IESVS, &amp; of all them whom in thy loue thou haſt giuen to him to be his brethren, it hath beene thy good pleaſure, to ſettle our true and only felicitie in the knowledge of thy holy name, and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of thy grace. But we are vnable to know thee, or to feele the efficacy of thy loue towards vs, but
<pb facs="tcp:24771:45"/>only in the ſame Chriſt, who is the brightneſſe of thy glory, and the engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen character of thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, God with thee, and man with vs. By this thy eternall word thou haſt created all the world, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto vs the firſt te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of thy wiſedome and prouidence. But thou giueſt vnto vs, a more ſingulare benefite in the miraculous worke of our redemption, which doeth moreouer repreſent vnto vs, both
<pb facs="tcp:24771:45"/>thy great goodneſſe and loue, and thy Iuſtice, &amp; infinit power. Thy loue, in that thou haſt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed freely to redeeme man, who prowde and vnthankefull, withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe from thee his Father and Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, to ſurrender him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto Sathan the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to our ſaluation, and of the honor of thy name. Thy Iuſtice, in that thou haſt not ſpared the blood of thy inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſonne, to the end in his ſufferings to iuſtifie
<pb facs="tcp:24771:46"/>thy goodneſſe and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. Thy power, in that for the accompliſhing of this ſupernatural worke, thy word, which from all eternitie was reſident in thy boſom, of one eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence &amp; glory with thee was made fleſh. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe I doe very well know, that the depth of theſe profound myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries cannot bee diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to our ſences, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that the treaſures of thy wiſedome, of thy counſell, &amp; of thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, are a very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:46"/>gulph, and thy wayes vnpoſſible to bee found out. Alſo, O Lord I doe not raſhly enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that place, which is forbidden mee, neither will I imitate my firſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Adam,</hi> who co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueting to knowe too much ſtretched forth his hand vnto the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den tree, &amp; deſiring one onely fruite, was depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of all the reſt. I doe onely with flexible heart embrace, and carefully in my cogitation, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:47"/>thy gifts, meditate vpon that ſecret of godlineſſe, which I haue receiued by the preaching of thy goſpell, and doe in part know it: attending, vntil that beeing deliuered from ſinne &amp; corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I may ſee thee face to face, and in preſence behold, that which now I ſee as it were in a very darke Glaſſe. I beſeech thee therefore, my God, vouchſafe, by the light of thy ſpirit, to addreſſe and guide mee to the faithfull knowledge of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:47"/>this great Sauior, whom thou (Father) haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and in the latter times reuealed, in ſignes and wonders ſurpaſſing all miracles, to the end that being inſtructed by his doctrine, I may, by him, and in him, know thee to be the eternall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, and the God of thy people, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his word I may worſhip and ſerue thee in ſpirit and trueth, and in his name call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee only in full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence
<pb facs="tcp:24771:48"/>of thy mercy, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compting him the onely ſubiect thereof, and the onely mediatour of my ſaluation, who died for my ſinnes, and roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for my righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: euen (O Lord) becauſe it pleaſed thee in this maner to ordaine of the eſtate of humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the worke of thy hand. For who was thy councellor? and what haue wee that wee haue not receiued? graunt me therfore in the ſtudy and meditation of ſo manie
<pb facs="tcp:24771:48"/>myſteries, ſo high and ſo wholeſome, that I may humbly condiſcend to thy diuine counſells, in worſhipping them with this reſolution of thy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, that I will not knowe any thing but Chriſt, neither poſſeſſe any thing but him, ſith that in him, the treaſures of all wiſdome doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and that they who lodge him in their harts, haue thee, O God, veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſent, and doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy thee and thy bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites. Make mee alſo to
<pb facs="tcp:24771:49"/>feele and confeſſe this neceſſitie common to all the children of <hi>Adam,</hi> that for the cancelling of this obligation, which held vs bound to eternal death (the iuſt reward of ſinne) wee were forced to haue this great King of heauen, holy, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and ſeperate from all ſinners, to be our high Prieſt, our ſacrifice and oblation, vppon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare of the croſſe, to the end, O Lord, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy vnſearchable decree, grounded vpon
<pb facs="tcp:24771:49"/>mercy &amp; iuſtice, thy wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued ſonne hauing to himſelfe vnited our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the bondſlaue of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, might leade it to the combate, directing it how to ouercome this great aduerſarie: And this hath he done, obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for vs the victory, when he brake the ſting of death, and the bonds of hell, and that hee roſe out of the ſepulchre, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying with him this hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature as the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtpeny of our hope, to thy right hand into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.
<pb facs="tcp:24771:50"/>Of this ſo ſingular a benefit, let the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance be alwaies before my face, that I may offer vnto thee (O my God) the ſacrifice of thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all the dayes of my life: ſo that hauing my redeemer for a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all obiect, and ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of my Faith, in the knowledge of thy name, I may throughly learne Chriſt, not onely to beleeue by his word the ſacred hiſtory of his conception and birth, with his office of a ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
<pb facs="tcp:24771:50"/>King, great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and perpetuall law-giuer of his church, alſo his paſſion, death, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and aſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo, that in ful aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance in his promiſes, I may appropriate to my ſelfe the gifts and graces which he purchaſed for vs, by fullfilling that charge that he had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from thee, O father, to th'end, through him, to make vs worthie of thy ſaluation: ſo as I may comfort and wholy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my ſelfe vpon his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience
<pb facs="tcp:24771:51"/>and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhewing forth and ſealing this my hope by good workes, to thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, O eternall God, and the peace of my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="prayer">
               <head>The ſixth Prayer, For obtaining the gift of the Holy-ghoſt.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>By the eternall Spirite, Christ hath offered him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to GOD, the Spirit
<pb facs="tcp:24771:51"/>which ſoundeth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found things of God: which alſo testifieth with our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that we are the children of God.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Heb. 9.1. Cor. 2. Rom. 8.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, wee doe learne in thy word (the vnchangeable trueth) how without confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any thing in the three perſons of thy moſt ſimple Deitie, or ſeparating the onelie and indiuiſible ſubſtance
<pb facs="tcp:24771:52"/>thereof, each perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth that which is proper to it ſelfe in the workes of thy hands, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie in that which concerneth our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So the beginning of all and euery action, is properly attributed vnto thee, O Father of the whole world, and to Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the wiſdome, the counſel, and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to diſpoſe all things, and to the Holy-ghoſt, the virtue and ſupporter of all thy workes. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whereunto we alſo
<pb facs="tcp:24771:52"/>doe acknowledge from thy loue, and from thy eternall decree, that which thou haſt proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for vs in thy ſonne (very God made very man) ſuch a mediatour and ſauiour, as was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for vs: and we do render vnto him the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the fulneſſe of thy loue towards vs, and of that perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which he hath yeel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded to thy ordinance, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the death of the croſſe for vs in moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter anguiſh, as alſo from
<pb facs="tcp:24771:53"/>the vertue of the Holy-ghoſt, wee doe confeſſe the efficacie, and health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full application of this great &amp; principal worke-manſhip of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>But thy wiſdome, O Lord, reſteth wholy in myſterie, that is to ſay, it is hidden, except vnto thoſe to whom thy ſpirit giueth ſight. For true it is, that Chriſt calleth all men vnto him by his Goſpel, ſpreading forth to that effect, his light throughout the whole
<pb facs="tcp:24771:53"/>world. Whoſo follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him, ſhall not walke in darkeneſſe; for hee is the Sunne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the way to go to heauen: But his ſheep only do heare his voice, and follow him; as alſo hee knoweth them and giueth vnto them life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting: euen by the meere efficacie of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which quickeneth &amp; lighteneth all thy elect, O God, to make them in thy word to behold the onely lampe of thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the knowledge of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:54"/>ſaluation, the ſtedfaſt good of the ſoule, and the ſure and only means to obtaine the ſame: all people may reade thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred writings, only they can gather the ſence to the peace of their ſoules, whom it pleaſeth thee, as a Father to illuminate from aboue. For ſo may they ſee howe in the croſſe of Ieſus they doe obtaine their triumph, in his ſhame, their glory, in his paine, their peace, in his teares, their ioy, in his ſorrowe, their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:54"/>in his death their life, in his reſurrection, the fulnes of their hope. I beſeech thee therefore, my God, to powre vpon me this thy ſpirit of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and reuelation, and grace, and mercie, through the force of his beames, to ſcatter the darkeneſſe of my vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and with the propertie of his fire, to purifie my peruerſe affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, with his celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all lamp to kindle in my hart the true zeale of his glorie, with his holie
<pb facs="tcp:24771:55"/>oyntment, to enbaulme my conſcience, with his ſacred oyle to reioyce and refreſh my bowells, and with his vertue to renew in me an vpright ſpirit, to the end that my ſoule thus cleanſed from the dead workes of the fleſh, may be repleniſhed with faith working all righteouſneſſe, whereby to ouercome all the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of my peace, (Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, the fleſh, the world, and my owne luſts.) But aboue al things, O Lord, make that by the efficacy
<pb facs="tcp:24771:55"/>of thy holy ſpirit, I may obtaine the true and firme conſolation of the faithful ſoule, the height of his ioy, of his quiet and content, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible direction to his perfection, namely, the aſſurance that thou, my heauenly Father, haſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted mee into the number of thy children, by that grace that thou haſt giuen vs in Chriſt, who was made our wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, righteouſneſſe, ſanctification, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. And that
<pb facs="tcp:24771:56"/>being ſo ouerſhadowed with the hope of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians which neuer at all confoundeth, I may bee ſupported, euen to the end of my dayes, by thy holy ſpirite, which then eſpecially may help my weakeneſſe, that I may yeeld vnto thee, O my God, my laſt groanes, to thee acceptable, and to me ſalutiferous, as being in the throne of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie approoued capable of the contemplation thereof in the heauenly <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> through thy
<pb facs="tcp:24771:56"/>goodneſſe and mercy in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord: To whom with thee, O Father, and the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, one onely God, bee all honor, glory, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion for euermore. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="prayer">
               <head>The ſeuenth Prayer, To craue of God the light of his word.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:57"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>God hauing at ſundrie times, and in diuers man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſpoken to our Fathers by the Prophets. In theſe last dayes hee hath ſpoken vnto vs by his Sonne. All Scripture is giuen from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue by inſpiration, and is profitable to teach, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, to correct, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct in righteouſneſſe, that the man of God may be accompliſhed, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly instructed to al good workes.</p>
                     <bibl>Heb. <hi>1.</hi> Tim. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ord GOD eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb facs="tcp:24771:57"/>that euerie man is but fleſh, and that fleſh is but corruption, ſo that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though thou haſt endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoule, which doth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh him, from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures, yet his light is notwithſtanding conuerted into darknes, when therby he ſeeketh to penetrate into the glorie of thy kingdome, and the myſteries of thy grace: who knowſt that this poore blind borne, deſtitute of thy ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall light, doeth in lieu
<pb facs="tcp:24771:58"/>of his God, forge to him ſelfe an idol, and inſtead of truth, taketh lies, for thy worde, his owne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, for goodneſſe vanitie, and for the path to life, the way to death. And albeit thou haſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from the beginning made thy ſelfe as it were viſible to man, in the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Vniuerſall worlde, that thou haſt many times reuealed thy ſelfe vnto him in a liuely voyce, by thy eternall worde in <hi>Heden, Horeb,</hi> in the burning buſh, and
<pb facs="tcp:24771:58"/>elſewhere, afterward by thy prophets inſinuating thy ſelfe by thy ſpirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their harts &amp; thoghts, to the end by their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie to inſtruct thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: and finally that thou haſt alſo manifeſted thy ſelfe in greater light by thy owne worde made fleſh for our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſpeaking vnto vs by his mouth: Yea which is more, that thou haſt ſo farre graced vs, that this thy word of life hath beene, and ſtil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth among vs, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb facs="tcp:24771:59"/>collected in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred regiſters of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture, ſo to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, the image of thy glory, the Lawe of thy Kingdome, the ladder to Heauen, the gate to paradice, the trumpet of ſaluation: to be briefe, the treaſury of piety, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, wiſdome, conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and perfection: Yet the fleſh neuertheleſſe ignorant, raſh, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, hath neither eyes to perceiue theſe ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all riches, nor eares to heare the wholſome do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:59"/>but dooth rather diſdaine it, as it were ſome deuiſed diſcourſe, &amp; vnprofitable voice: or howſoeuer it be, ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf to be carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with it owne &amp; fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble imaginations, taketh in this verely, the thorne for the roſe, the leafe for the fruite, and the huske for the kernell. And thus are wee all borne in this error, in this calamitie, in this waie to mortall ruine, vntill that thou, O mercifull God, makeſt vs to be borne againe, of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:60"/>the ſpirite, and in will to make our thoughts capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the light of thy word; &amp; through true faith, to apprehend the myſteries of thy kingdome, the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of life, the goſpel of thy peace, and the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured teſtimonies of thy mercies. Vnto this grace of ineſtimable valewe doth my timerous ſoule direct her vowes in ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thee (O great king of Heauen) throughout the courſe of thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full teſtimonies, which miniſter wiſedome to
<pb facs="tcp:24771:60"/>the ignorant [the holie Scriptures] I beſeech thee therfore (my God) vouchſafe to direct and guide mee in the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of this eternall trueth, through the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thy ſpirit, (the true teacher of our ſoules) that being by him inſtructed, I may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh and make my ſelfe perfect in theſe foure cheefe principles of the doctrine of Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which are fullie taught at large. (The knowledge of thee the
<pb facs="tcp:24771:61"/>true God, and the God of thy people: the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of faith, of pietie, and of righteouſneſſe.) Whereby I may obtaine the end of my being, and therein euen my Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne felicitie, which is to know thee, to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thee for my GOD, to beleeue thee, and in thee, Ieſus Chriſt, and in Ieſus Chriſt, to loue, feare, and ſerue thee, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as thou doeſt commaund vs, and in all things to obſerue equity towardes all men. For
<pb facs="tcp:24771:61"/>thus are thy children bound to learne, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of the gift of thy grace, thy fatherly loue, in thy wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued ſonne, namelie by conioyning thereto the feare of thy name; that is to ſay, that reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that cauſeth vs in humilitie, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to ſhunne euil, and do good, and to embrace righteouſneſſe, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Walking in this ſort, O Lord, vnder thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, in the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints, I ſhall want
<pb facs="tcp:24771:62"/>nothing to my comfort or perfection; &amp; in good time, a depart (my life beeing ended) to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue peace and perfect ioy, in the eternall habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the bleſſed ſoules. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="prayer">
               <head>The eight Prayer, That we may not depart from the Church.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:62"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Christ hath loued the Church, and giuen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for her, to the end hee might ſanctifie her, after he hath purged hir by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of water, through the word. Shee is the houſe of God, the prop and piller of truth: the gates of hel ſhall not preuaile againſt her.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Eph. 5.1. Tim. 3. Ma. 16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmighty God, righteous, and mercifull, who in thy iuſtice &amp; wrath, for the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb facs="tcp:24771:63"/>and diſobedience of man diddeſt once ſmite the world with the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing of waters, and in thy mercie and loue diddeſt extend thy ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular fauour vppon the Arke of thy ſeruant <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> ſauing him and his family from the generall inundation, intending in that ſmall flocke of the faithfull to preſerue and keepe thy choſen people that they might for euer ſerue to thy glory I learn out of thy word, that thou wilt no more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb facs="tcp:24771:63"/>the earth in that maner, and therefore thou haſt left vs the rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow to remaine for a ſigne. Neuertheleſſe what elſe is our poore life languiſhing in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of ſinne, but a deluge of euills, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſtreame of miſeries that falleth vpon al men, &amp; indifferently leadeth them vnto death? In one onelie thing therefore muſt my ſoule take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that as <hi>Noah</hi> was preſerued from the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall ſhipwracke, in his
<pb facs="tcp:24771:64"/>wodden Manſion by the promiſe that he kept in his heart, ſo that a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand falling on his right hand, and a thouſand on his left hand, hee remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſound and ſafe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy wing, euen ſo I hold my ſelfe aſſured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the aſſaults of ſin, and in the middeſt of the woefull rockes of this world, yea euen in the ſtraits of the graue, that thou wilt alwayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue from all calamities and miſeries, thoſe who ſtand faſt in the Arke of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:64"/>thy Church, grounded vppon thy word in the goſpel of reconciliation to the Lord Ieſus, and depart in his faith. For as likewiſe, according to thy Iuſtice, thou diddeſt euen from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning pronounce the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death againſt our Fathers, becauſe of their tranſgreſſions, euen ſo it pleaſed thee, euen then alſo to comforte them in thy mercie, with the promiſe of life in this great Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer to come, to the end,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:65"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:24771:65"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:24771:66"/>that embracing him by faith, they and their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren holding this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, ſhould erect vnto thee a temple of liuing ſtones, holy, and ſtedfaſt for euer, for the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of thy name, and the bleſſedneſſe of thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. And theſe are they (O Lord) who firſt in the time of the Patriarks, then vnder the law, and laſtly, vnder the goſpel, beleeued thy word, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping thee according to the ſame, in certaine myſteries of religion,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:66"/>in all places, whither it pleaſed thee to call, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſanctifie them, by the remiſſion of their ſinnes, in the blood of thy ſonne, regenerating them to euery good worke, by thy holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, &amp; of the ſame grace, giuing them from age to age diuerſe viſible ſignes for ſacraments in thy Church; ſo indeede ſhe is thy houſe, and the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of thy glory, where thy truth is lodged, which ſhee vpholdeth and aduaunceth by her
<pb facs="tcp:24771:67"/>holy miniſtery; preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it alſo that it ſhould not fall into decay, and that the remembrance thereof ſhould not bee loſt from among men. Whereof likewiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth the ſtabilitie of the Church, which the endeuours of ſathan can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſhake, becauſe the foundation of her faith &amp; doctrine is grounded vpon the true, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooueable rocke, euen the pure confeſſion of the name of Chriſt. I do therefore beſeech thee,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:67"/>my God, inaſmuch as thy mercy and goodnes hath brought me in, and hetherto held me vp, in this manſion houſe of thy graces, that thou wilt vouchſafe more &amp; more to illuminate my hart &amp; minde, to make me ſee and meditate vpon the ſpirituall magnificence of this thy habitation, to the end that the ſacred porches thereof may bee all my loue, and the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delight of my eyes, &amp; her canticles the ſole har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my eares: and
<pb facs="tcp:24771:68"/>that I may ſo affectionate my ſelfe to her celeſtiall beauty and riches, that I may hold one day in thy Church more deere, then a thouſand elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. That this ſo ſweet company, I ſay, of thee (O our Father) of thy Sonne our redeemer, of the holy-ghoſt our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, of ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Angels, &amp; of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, which liuedhere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath in the viſible king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of thy glory, and by infinite wonders in the Communion of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:68"/>ſaints, may be my whole deſire, and the ſole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of my delights, that I may neuer depart ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, notwithſtanding whatſoeuer aſſaults and temptations I am to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure according to the condition of the militant Church, and vnder this her gallant poeſie <hi>(To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, to doe well, and to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer affliction)</hi> ſith that namely there is not any ſuch miſhap, or ſo much to be feared, as to be out of this holie Temple, wherein onely abideth
<pb facs="tcp:24771:69"/>all light, truth, ſaluation, and life: and in all other places, darkeneſſe, lying, ſhipwracke, and death, haue their dwelling. For ſo through thy grace, O my God, praying and meditating, I ſhall ſpend my dayes in ioy, expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in peace, my laſt hower, to participate in the triumph of the ſame Church aboue, and to liue eternally in thy reſt, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:69"/>
               <head>The ninth Prayer, For the obtaining of the efficacie of holy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Ieſus comming to his Diſciples, ſpake vnto them ſaying: All power is giuen vnto me both in heauen &amp; in earth. Goe yee therefore, and teach all nations, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing them, in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy-ghoſt, and teaching them to obſerue all that I haue commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Mat. 28.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:70"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall God, only good, &amp; wiſe, thou haſt vouchſafed by thy Sonne, that great prophet, to teach vs, that whoſoeuer is not borne of water and the ſpirite, cannot enter into thy kingdome; and that fleſh and blood are not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the ſight of thy glorie. Thou, O Lord, art eſſentially holineſſe and righteouſnes. How then can vncleaneneſſe, and iniuſtice approach
<pb facs="tcp:24771:70"/>neere vnto thee? So it is that wee are by our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture corrupted, and by ſinne polluted, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Sentence of death, both firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, hath ouertaken all men; howbeit, of thy infinite mercy, thou haſt vouchſafed to ſaue from a gulph of miſeries, thoſe that in thy vnſearchable counſaile are predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to life, redeeming them from hell, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them to bee borne againe in Ieſus Chriſt, thy eternall woorde, by
<pb facs="tcp:24771:71"/>the which thou haddeſt firſt giuen them beeing. And theſe are they that are borne of water and the ſpirit into thy church through the efficacie of the ſacred myſteries of thy grace, &amp; ſpecially of holie Baptiſme; that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clothed anew in the nature and righteouſnes of Chriſt their Sauiour, they may become new creatures, pure and preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous before thee. Nowe through thy great mercy (O my God) I haue, in thy holy Temple, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:24771:71"/>this ſacred pledge of thy couenant, and of our new birth in thy name, and in the name of thy Sonne, and of the Holy-ghoſt, according to thy ordinance, as it hath pleaſed thee in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of thy Church, by the preaching of the Goſpel, to manifeſt thy ſelfe farre more cleerely in three perſons of thy deitie, then vnder the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures and ſhadowes of the Law. For in Chriſt, repleniſhed with grace and trueth, thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:24771:72"/>made thy ſelfe viſible, who hath reuealed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and the Holy Ghoſt alſo, by plentifully ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the beames of his glory vpon vs, through the brightneſſe of his works, altogether diuine and miraculous. Wee cannot ſo much as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the vertue and efficacy of the ſacrament of baptiſme, vnleſſe wee begin by the meditation of thy free mercie in thy Sonne, and ſo doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him, performing
<pb facs="tcp:24771:72"/>his office, euen ſo farre forth, as to die for vs: and with him wee doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne the Holy-Ghoſt, through whome Chriſt dooth waſh vs in his blood, regenerateth vs, and maketh vs partakers of all his benefits. This, O Lord, I knowe by thy word, that like as the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of baptiſme is vnto mee a certaine ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt penie of my ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo muſt it in my own conſcience, and before men, be vnto mee a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall teſtimonie of my
<pb facs="tcp:24771:73"/>faith and of my hope. So onely dooth this ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment obtaine his perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and fulnes, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when that ſhadowed in the waſhing of my body with the ſigne of water, is effectually wrought within my ſoule, throughout the whole courſe of my life. For in like manner was the ſhadow of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant fulfilled, in cutting awaie the fore-skinne from the Children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> when by the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of their harts,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:73"/>they became carefull to walke in the ſtatutes of Gods Lawe. I beſeech thee therefore, O my God, as I carrie in my forehead the holy marke of Chriſtians, ſo vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe, with thy finger, to graue in my hart this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Character, to the ende that I may euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more beare and bring forth ſuch fruite and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, as may be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in thy ſight, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to my ſelfe; that as my Lord Ieſus, by his ſpirite working in mee,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:74"/>waſheth away my ſinnes and regenerateth my ſoule, ſo I may likewiſe, by the efficacie of his owne vertue, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing from him, grace, perſeuere in the faith of my Baptiſme, readie to euery good worke. And that as I was baptiſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his death, ſo likewiſe to be buried with him, by being dead vnto ſin, ſo that I may bee grafted with him to the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his reſurrection in glory, liuing no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to ſinne, but to righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:74"/>whereby thy name, O eternall God, may be ſanctified, and I crowned in my latter day with the crowne of immortalitie amongeſt the company of thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ones. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="prayer">
               <head>The tenth Prayer, ¶ For the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the holy Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:75"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Ieſus tooke bread, and when he had giuen thanks, he brake it, and gaue it to his diſciples and ſaid; Take, eate, this is my body. Then taking the cup, and giuing thankes, hee gaue it them, ſaying, Drinke yee all, for this is my blood, the blood of the Newe Teſtament, which is ſhed for many to the remiſsion of ſinnes.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ma. 26.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmightie &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting god, according to thy loue and
<pb facs="tcp:24771:75"/>infinite goodneſſe, it hath pleſaed thee, that not onely to redeeme vs from ſinne, from death, and from hell, and in all points to make vs bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, thy onely ſonne (the brightneſſe and fulneſſe of thy glory) ſhould take vpon him humane fleſh, and after hee had taught vs the way to heauen, ſhould die vppon the croſſe, for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of his office, but alſo that this great benefite might ſtill bee preſent to our perpetuall
<pb facs="tcp:24771:76"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:24771:76"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:24771:77"/>comfort, and for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and ſupport of our faith, that his body riſen againe in glory for our righteouſneſſe and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, aſcended into heauen, and ſitting at thy right hand, ſhould alſo bee communicated vnto vs here beneath in thy Church, in the myſtery of the Euchariſt, to bee our foode and nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto holy and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life. Thus is there ſealed in our hearts that promiſe that hee hath made vnto vs in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:77"/>that hee will, at all times, make vs partakers of his fleſh and of his blood, and in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion giue vnto vs the true and ſound foode of our ſoules, that in him (who is the liuing bread, diſcended from heauen) wee may obtaine our peace and felicitie. O mightie prouidence of the Lord, who called vs to communicate in his body before his death, to the end to ſhew vs, that by death he ſhould not be deſtroyed, and that he
<pb facs="tcp:24771:78"/>would neuer leaue his Church; O what a refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing is this, in this our earthly pilgrimage, and what a delicious ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, in the bread and wine, conſecrated by the word of Chriſt, to eate his glorious fleſh, and to drinke his precious blood: when by faith in his promiſes, and by the vertue of his holy ſpirit, hauing our hearts cleanſed and lifted vp on high, his life, together with all his graces and bleſſings is made ours! O
<pb facs="tcp:24771:78"/>infinite bleſſed is that flocke that hath ſo libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral a ſhepheard, that will noriſh it with his bloud, to the end it may liue in him, and of him, free from all languiſhing and miſerie! O what a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is it in this vally of teares, to finde meanes to feede vpon ſuch food as will not periſh, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce all our ſences, and make vs to liue eternally! For ſo and with ſuch effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie (O Lord) doe wee communicate in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of thy Sonne crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:24771:79"/>and riſen againe, and in his bloud ſhed for the waſhing of our ſoules, when at his holie Table the ſacred ſignes are, by his ordinance, deliuered vnto vs, and that we doe receiue them as hee hath commanded, expecting that aboue in heauen without any exterior meanes, we may eate this bread of life, and drinke this ſweete drinke in the company of the Angels, &amp; of all the bleſſed, then at the ful inioying of our vnion with thee, O great
<pb facs="tcp:24771:79"/>God, and the ioy of our beatitude accompliſhed. O moſt deſired daie, wherein we ſhall be fed and ſatisfied with this celeſtiall bread, that we may neuer die, nor thirſt againe in this newe life, where thou, O eternall God, ſhalt bee wholy in vs. Oh happie are wee already, who already in Chriſt, in the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the faithfull, do taſte the ſweetnes of this celeſtiall banquet, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ſhall ſee thee, and face to face contemplate
<pb facs="tcp:24771:80"/>[Father, Word, Spirit] one only and true God, beeing filled with thy glory in endleſſe peace. To the end therfore that according to thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, O Lord, I may worthily preſent my ſelf to this holy ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet of ſacred foode, which the Angelles doe admire, and honour, which alſo thou doſt not communicate but to thy fleſh, I beſeech thee giue mee grace well to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the bodie of my Sauiour, in trying my
<pb facs="tcp:24771:80"/>ſelfe according to his word, ſo as my hart may be cleanſed from ſinne, and vncleaneneſſe, and repleniſhed with thy loue, and with euery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirituall vertue, to the end, that euen this day, harbouring therein this great King of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, I may encreaſe in the faith and hope of my ſaluation, by his holines and righteouſneſſe. I haue repoſed al my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in thy mercy, I neither ſeeke nor hope for any good or grace,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:81"/>but from thee (my God) and in thy ſonne, and for his ſake, I doe deſire in my place, with ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, to celebrate the remembrance of his death in the holy church to the glory of thy name, and the peace of my ſoule. I renounce the deadworkes of the fleſh, and the luſts thereof, I doe put off all enmitie and malice, with a good intent to embrace the liuely workes of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and to dwell in loue and charitie with my
<pb facs="tcp:24771:81"/>neighbours, I do belieue in the promiſes that Chriſt (the infallible truth) hath pronounced with his owne mouth; That at his holy table, he will truely make me par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of his body and blood, to the end I may poſſeſſe him wholy, and in ſuch ſorte, that being made fleſh of his fleſh, and bone of his bone, he may liue in mee, aad I in him for euer. Helpe O Lord the weakeneſſe of my faith, ſupport mee in my infirmity, and in that
<pb facs="tcp:24771:82"/>deſire which thou giueſt me, to profit in the ſound knowledge of thy my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, and in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the pathes of thy kingdome, conioyne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame deſire, the performaunce of the deede. For it is onely by the vertue of thy ſpirit, in ſinceritie of heart, that I ſhall this day receiue from the ſame Ieſus, the effect of his word, in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipating truely in his new and eternall teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the couenant of grace, ſo to perſeuer in
<pb facs="tcp:24771:82"/>this bleſſed ſocietie of his Bodie, that from him I may inceſſantly gather ſtrength and life, and vnited with him, I may alſo attaine to bee one with thee (my Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator.) Grant mee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that in this maner I may, with thy Church, celebrate the moſt holy remembrance of our Lord, and of the worke of our redemption, to the end, that ſo receuing this great ſacrament of his body, with a newe augmentation in all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie
<pb facs="tcp:24771:83"/>grace, with ſo much the greater confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence I may againe call vpon thee my God, and my Father, and more &amp; more glorifie my ſelfe in thy mercies. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="prayer">
               <head>The eleuenth Prayer, For thankſgiuing after the Communion.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:83"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>And when they had ſung a Pſalme, they went out vnto the Mount of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liues.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Mat. 26.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lorde, my God, &amp; my Father, euen from the bottome of my heart, and with all my ſoule, I yeelde thee praiſe and thankes, for that it hath pleaſed thee to enlarge ſo great a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite to mee miſerable ſinner, as to haue drawn,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:84"/>and receiued mee into the ſacred Communion of thy ſon Ieſus Chriſt my ſauiour. The heauen of heauens are not able to comprehend him, yet doth he ſo farre honour vs, as to vouchſafe to communicate with vs, yea euen to enter into vs (poore wormes of the earth.) For ſuch was thy good pleaſure, (O Lord) to deliuer him once to the death, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of thy elect; and as to euery one of them, ſo doeſt thou this
<pb facs="tcp:24771:84"/>day giue him to mee, to be my foode and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſuſtenance, that I may liue of him, and in him, bleſſed both in body &amp; ſoule eternally. I beſeech thee therefore, O merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father, ſo to bleſſe in me, this holy and myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call action, that my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſſe make it not vnprofitable vnto me, &amp; that the pretious bloud of thy ſonne, bee not in vaine ſhed for mee, and offered me to drinke: but that waſhed in the ſame, and cleanſed from
<pb facs="tcp:24771:85"/>my ſinnes, I may obtain that iuſtification, and holines, that beſeemeth thy children, who haue this moſt holy one to be their hoſte, and head, &amp; thy ſpirit for their light. Let me not be ſo wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, as to abuſe theſe ſacred meates, which thou doſt communicate to thy houſhold of faith onely, the prouiſion whereof coſt thy welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued ſon Ieſus ſo deere. Rather (my God) grant that in true efficacie I may participate in this
<pb facs="tcp:24771:85"/>ſacrament of his body to encreaſe in faith &amp; loue, and all other thy gifts, that I may neuer aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thy holy couenant. Alas! whither ſhould I go but to thee, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of eternall life, by Chriſt, who is the fulnes thereof, and by whom it runneth into vs? Caſt from me all carnall cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and delights, and all theſe earthly baites, which turne to gall and corruption, becauſe I haue in my bowels an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible foode, more
<pb facs="tcp:24771:86"/>ſweeter then honny, the bread of Angels, the bread of heauen, the bread of life, which with out any ſacrament wee ſhall feede on aboue, without ende; where Chriſt, according to his promiſe, ſhall, with vs, drinke the fruite of the new vine, yeelding vppe vnto thee, the kingdome, O eternal God, that thou maiſt be all in all. I doe therefore reſigne my ſelf into thy hands, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy conduct, that I may runne my race in
<pb facs="tcp:24771:86"/>ioy, and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence before thy face, and before men: And that I may departe in peace, when my houre is come becauſe Chriſt is my life. To thy name therefore, (O almighty Creator) to thee Redeemer of the elect, to thee Comforter of the faithfull, who by thy ſecret vertue doeſt worke this vnſpeakeable and miraculous coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our ſoules with the body of the Lord. To thee Trinity (Father, Word, Spirit) one only
<pb facs="tcp:24771:87"/>and true God, be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="prayer">
               <head>The twelfth Praier, To obtaine the gift of Faith.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>The law was our ſchool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maister, to bring vs to Christ, that wee might bee iustified by faith. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> beleeued in God, and it was imputed to him for righteouſneſſe: Yee all are
<pb facs="tcp:24771:87"/>the children of God by the faith that is in Ieſus Chriſt</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Galath. 3. Rom. 4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmightie and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal god, it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee in thy vnſearchable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, for a time, to giue vnto men, the Lawe, to the end to guide them to IESVS Chriſt, vnder a ſchoolehouſe of figures and ſhadows, euen thoſe whom thou of thy grace haſt called into the faith
<pb facs="tcp:24771:88"/>of this promiſed Sauior, to obtaine in him their iuſtification and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And when in the fulneſſe of time hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared vnto vs, clothed in our nature, for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing of thy great and precious promiſes, this iuſtification of thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect was fully reuealed &amp; made ours, by beleefe in his Goſpel. But, O Lord, thou dooſt well know, and euery man in himſelfefeeleth, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulitie, and weaknes of man, who being but
<pb facs="tcp:24771:88"/>earth, and fleſh, cannot climbe vp into heauen, and to the ſpirit of life, ſo to confeſſe and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend theſe deepe myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of thy loue. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is an ancient and common complaint of thy Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who manie times haue ſaid as much (O Lord who hath belieued our preaching?) Alſo there be ſo many impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures in the worlde, ſo many dreames, ſo many inuentions; yea which is more, ſo many aſſaults,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:89"/>ſo many ſnares, and ſo ordinary miſeries that ſhake the beſt: To bee briefe, ſo great is the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, ignorance, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie of our nature, that if thou (O moſt mercifull God) workeſt not that in vs, which thou commaundeſt vs to doe, if thou dooſt not teach vs that vvee may knowe, if thou dooſt not conuert vs, that wee may cleaue to thy worde, if thou doſt not giue vs to thy Sonne, that hee may keepe vs thine, if hee
<pb facs="tcp:24771:89"/>bring vs not cloathed in his righteouſneſſe to the throne of thy grace, and if thy ſpirite leadeth vs not in the paths of thy Kingdome, holding vs faſt in the effects of his gifts, vppon the way of thy trueth, wee cannot harken to this voyce of the ſhepheard of our ſoules, neither in our harts conceiue ſuch and ſo liuely a Faith, that all vncertainty might be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and the ſame ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with his owne effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie: much leſſe can
<pb facs="tcp:24771:90"/>we feele the peace and ioy that true faith bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with it. For that cauſe, (O Lord,) in thy loue haſt thou promiſed to poure vpon thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſeruants this ſpirite of thy ſtrength, light, mercy, and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to forme in their heartes this thy ſingular gift, which vnto vs, is a ſubſiſtance of the things that wee hope for, and a demonſtration of thoſe that wee ſee not. By this ſo holy and neceſſarie an ornament of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:90"/>wee doe in all aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, crie vnto thee, <hi>[Abba, Father,]</hi> and in our conſciences feele, that wee are at peace with thy maieſty, throgh Chriſt, beeing iuſtified in his blood, that wee may liue religiouſly and holily according to his worde. I doe therefore beſeech thee, my GOD, to accompliſh, in my ſoule, theſe great effects of thy loue, newe cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing me with the light and vertue of thy holie ſpirit, that after the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:24771:91"/>of the gift thereof, I may be able, with a true and liuely faith, to pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate into the ſecret of my calling, and to that end, vouchſafe ſo to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in mee this faith, that by the degrees of the perfection thereof, it may appeare in all her fruites, cauſing mee to worſhip, inuocate, and ſerue thee according as thou commandeſt, that my vnderſtanding may be withdrawne from the ſeduction of errour, and my wil from carnal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:91"/>alſo that my hart may infinitely bee comforted with the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of this, that by chriſt I am reconciled to thee to holineſſe of life, and eternal beatitude: ſo that dayly encreaſing in this all ſpiritual vertue, I may attaine to ſome portion of thy Soueraigne wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and perfect righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, to the ende, that when my ſoule ſhall forſake this fleſhly habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, the ſame faith may be as wings to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port it into thy boſome,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:92"/>to the celeſtial reſt of the Angels and Saints, there to poſſeſſe the fulnes of her peace, and of all ioy. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="prayer">
               <head>The thirteenth Prayer. To demaund the vertue of hope.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>God, by his great mercy, hath regenerated vs to a liuely hope, by the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Ieſus Christ from
<pb facs="tcp:24771:92"/>the dead. To the end, that being iuſtified by his grace, we ſhould be made heires according to the hope of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, which hope ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs not aſhamed.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 Pet. 1. Tim. 3. Rom. 5.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> GOD, all good and wiſe, it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee, by certaine meanes, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, to work in thy elect, regeneration ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for their ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whereby they do in
<pb facs="tcp:24771:93"/>themſelues feele the old <hi>Adam</hi> to die with his luſts, and the newe man to encreaſe in the deſires of righteouſneſſe, when the Holi-ghoſt euen this day plucketh out of their hearts, vice, and inſteade thereof, planteth vertue, making it to bring forth fruite, furthering therby daily, the rooting out of ſin, and encreaſe of the gifts of thy grace. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee (O Lorde) that as it hath pleaſed thee, freely to iuſtifie me by the ſingular gift of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:93"/>faith in our Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, granting me peace with thy Maieſtie through his ſacrifice: ſo thou wouldſt vouchſafe to illuminate the eyes of my ſoule, as to make mee knowe, to the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of thy name, what the hope of thoſe is, whome thou haſt called to the incorruptible in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of thy glorie. Graunt (my God) that my thoughts may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed and contented with this ſtedfaſt hope in thy loue, which thou
<pb facs="tcp:24771:94"/>offereſt vnto vs in the goſpel, with this holie deſire, I ſay, ſupported with an aſſured expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion one day, and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to obtaine the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial riches, which thou haſt graunted mee to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, which no eie hath ſeen, no eare hath heard, nor no vnderſtanding hath comprehended: namely, that I may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to behold thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and liue, to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate without ende, thy kingdome aboue, to enioy there the ſocietie
<pb facs="tcp:24771:94"/>of the angels, to be there a fellow heire, with the glorified ſpirits: Finaly, there to bee fully vnited vnto Chriſt, &amp; by him, to thee, O Father, the fountaine of eternal life, and ſo to poſſeſſe the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne good eternaly. Let this holie meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the hope to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy that full and perfect contentment, ſo occupy my ſenſes, that it may be my thought, my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, my labour, my ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, and my moſt ordinary vacation. Alſo
<pb facs="tcp:24771:95"/>that all the cares of the world, and the affections of my fleſh, which might diuert mee from ſo chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian a reſolution, may giue place to this ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al vertue, the anker wher of reſteth in heauen, that it may lodge wholy and for euer in the ſecret of my heart; ſith it is verie true that it will yeeld as certainely his ſolide and ſole good, in fulneſſe of time, as if already I did poſſeſſe it, vniting mee vnto thee, (O Lord) by the holy miſteries of thy
<pb facs="tcp:24771:95"/>grace. Alſo thou art the beginning and the ende of our hope of eternall life, becauſe thy loue is powred vpon vs by the Holighoſt, whom thou haſt giuen vs, and thy Sonne Ieſus is the mean and fulneſſe, according as in him doth remaine all that is beautifull, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable, peaceable, rich, permanent, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aboue in Heauen, which thou haſt promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs. Of which trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ineſtimable va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lew, thou doeſt thus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:24771:96"/>already graunt mee the vſe, by the effects of thy diuine vertues, which make mee to pierce through the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens with my imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to eſtabliſh my ſoule in thy peace, as if in my boſome I kept the full fruit of thy promiſe, and did alreadie liue there aboue in like eſtate as the Angells. For (O eternall God) thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is vpon me, as I doe truſt in thee. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, albeit I creepe here vp and downe, through
<pb facs="tcp:24771:96"/>manie infirmities; Yet will I in patience abide the appearing of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the daie of the comming of thy Sonne, to iudge the quicke and the dead, as being tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly aſſured, through thy grace, in the end of my courſe, to obtain the diadem wherewith thou crowneſt thine; and at the laſt day, and euer in my fleſh, to behold that great Sauiour of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, who liueth with thee and the Holyghoſt one god eternally <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:97"/>
               <head>The fourteenth Prayer, To obtaine the vertue of Loue.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>God is loue, and he that dwelleth in loue, dwelleth in God, and God in him. The end of the Law is loue out of a pure heart, and a good conſcience, and faith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1. Ioh. 4. 1. Tim. 1.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall, who art al loue, and who accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb facs="tcp:24771:97"/>vertue thereof haſt loued vs before we wer, as alſo ſince the time that wee were thy enemies, vnthankefull ſinners; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged to death, and to the paines of hell, thou haſt, I ſay, freely ſo loued vs, that thou haſt giuen thy onely ſonne to the world, to redeeme vs, with the price of his blood, and for vs to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe righteouſneſſe, and a bleſſed life. This being ſo, O Lord, the original and fountaine of loue, make it with efficacy &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:24771:98"/>reflection to ſhine into al places, whither the knowledge of thy grace ſhall come; likewiſe, that where thou doeſt more neerely communicate thy ſelfe, by making the flames of thy loue to bee more liuely felt, graunt alſo, that there by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of thy ſpirit, the greater loue towardes thee may appeare. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee make mee more and more to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate and comprehend this thy admirable loue, that I may accordingly
<pb facs="tcp:24771:98"/>frame my ſelfe, to that loue thou requirſt of thy children, &amp; truely faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which is alſo the end of the whole law, and precepts of the goſpell: So that in pureneſſe of heart, with an vpright conſcience, and with a true and liuely faith, I may attaine to the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of thy truth and will, to the end, in all, &amp; through al, to obey thee with a quiet conſcience, the ſame being the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, the higheſt, and the moſt perfect degree of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:99"/>loue, that we can teſtifie vnto thee (O our God) and that which leadeth vs to the perfection of Chriſtian life, which of mortall men maketh vs as it were Angels, which albeit wee liue vppon earth, maketh vs Citti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens of heauen: to bee briefe, it is that which in the ſecret of our hearts, giueth vs a ſweet feeling of thy peace, which ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth all the reaſon of our vnderſtanding. That alſo thereby I may learne, that there is none
<pb facs="tcp:24771:99"/>that can loue thee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, vntill he hath bin preuented by the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy vnmeaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble loue, and kindled with the flame. That we loue thee; becauſe thou firſt louedſt vs, &amp; like as alſo through thy grace thou makeſt thy ſelfe &amp; thy benefites knowne vnto vs. The more there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that wee finde our ſelues diſpoſed to loue thee, the more ſhuld we beleeue that thou makeſt thy ſelfe to be felt in the inwarde partes of our
<pb facs="tcp:24771:100"/>ſoules, to bee our God and our Father, and that therefore wee haue the greater cauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and comfort our ſelues in the loue that thou beareſt vs. O Lord make me alſo to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that as Chriſtian charitie doth eſpecially regard and looke vppon thy holy deitie (Father, Son, and Holy-ghoſt) one onely God, that we may loue thee with our whole hearts, mindes, and ſtrengths: ſo hath ſhee a like regard to her
<pb facs="tcp:24771:100"/>neighbour, that in thee, and for thy ſake, becauſe he beareth thy image, we may loue him as our ſelues: for in theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned and reciprocall things alſo Chriſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs the bond of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, euen that wee ſhall indeede be his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, if we loue one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, becauſe he ſo ſhal fullfill his loue in our hearts. But being, O Lord, very true, that the faith which thou giueſt vs doth ſingularly vnite thy familie together,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:101"/>graunt me the ſpirite of loue, which leading me to doe well to all men, doth teach me principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to loue the houſhold of thy Church, that I may with a ready will, yeelde them all helpe in their neceſſities. In aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much alſo as our redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer (the perfect pattern of charitie) hath loued his enemies, procuring them good for euill, and bleſſing for iniurie, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, my GOD, giue me grace, to extend my loue to thoſe that
<pb facs="tcp:24771:101"/>hate mee, that without hypocriſie, or vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, I may, to my power, help forward their good and ſaluation. And ſo that I may beare an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and lowly heart to all men, whereby all the faithfull may be edefied and comforted; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſeeing my good works, rather thine than mine, may be conſtraind to glorifie thee, <hi>O our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which art in heauen. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:102"/>
               <head>The fifteenth Prayer, That we may well vſe afflictions.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>If any man will follow me, let him forſake him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and take vp his croſſe and follow me. By manie tribulations wee muſt enter into the Kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Hee chastizeth him whom he loueth, and ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth euerie childe that hee receiueth.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Mat. 16. Act. 14. Heb. 12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:102"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, my GOD and my father, I learne in thy worde that none be true Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Ieſus Chriſt, but they that followe his ſteppes, wherof he hath deliuered vs a ſure marke in theſe two chief points (the renouncing of our ſelues, and the volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie enduring of the croſſe.) For naturallie we are inueagled, with a diſorderly loue to our
<pb facs="tcp:24771:103"/>ſelues, and doe preſume too much of our owne perſons. It is therefore neceſſarie for vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce our own nature and reaſon, and to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don our owne affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to ſuffer thee &amp; thy loue (O our God) to liue &amp; raigne in vs. Then muſt we proceede to the other point, that is, cheerefully to beare out the afflictions and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this life, wherein it pleaſeth thee eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to exerciſe thine, vpon diuerſe good conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:103"/>namely to make them conformeable to the image of thy Sonne, to the end, that ſuffering with him, they may alſo raigne in his glory. For it is very true, that al men by ſinne, doe eate the fruites of the earth in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and bread in the ſweate of their browes: that they all liue in a ſea, toſſed with many ſtormes, &amp; croſſed with many anguiſhes. But all haue not the gift of thy ſpirit, to learne by his doctrine, that the bread
<pb facs="tcp:24771:104"/>of affliction doeth nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh and ſtrengthen the faithfull ſoule, that the cup of bitterneſſe is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto a ſweet and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome drinke, and all tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation a ſpirituall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decine, to purge it from the leauen of ſinne, and ſo to forme euery true Chriſtian to godlineſſe and holineſſe of life.</p>
               <p>For indeede the ſundry temptations thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren do endure, are not properly a puniſhment for ſinne, but profitable corrections of thy hand,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:104"/>to make the triall of their faith to redound to their commendation &amp; profit that their hope may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in the expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the beatitude to come, that their loue may kindle, through the Fatherly care that thou takeſt of them, in hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them vnder the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of thy diſcipline, and that they may bee the more pricked forward to pray vnto thee feruently, and more and more to reuerence thy power. But principally that they
<pb facs="tcp:24771:105"/>comfort themſelues in this leſſon of the Apoſtle (that the eaſie afflictions of thine, which doe but euen paſſe ouer them, do bring forth an eternall weight of moſt excellent glorie.) True it is, that by the miſeries of this world, the outward man declineth, but on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, the inwarde man reneweth himſelfe with grace in the goods of the ſoule, ſo long vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till by degree hee be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed and obtaine his perfection. So that
<pb facs="tcp:24771:105"/>if our bodies doe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, our ſoules doe quicken, if wee ſuſtaine loſſe of terreſtiall things, thou (O Lord) doſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto vs thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen; and if this affliction befall, that any man put vs to death, he doth but haſten our paſſage to the true eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and bleſſed being. I beſeech thee therefore (O mercifull Father) to giue mee grace to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, and well to taſte ſo many ſweete and profitable fruits, as theſe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:106"/>thy Fatherly corrections doe bring with them: conſtantly meditating, that the eyes of thoſe that looke vnto thee in a chriſtian hope, doe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer faile, that their expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation hath not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded them, that the number of thy conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue ſurmounted their ſorrowes: and that the end of thy viſitation hath alwayes beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and happy vnto them. For thou delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in mercy, and thy compaſſion is vppon all
<pb facs="tcp:24771:106"/>thoſe that call vpon thee in their diſtreſſe. Let therefore the inuocation of thy name be vnto me a ſtrong tower, to defend me againſt all feare, and temptation, as being aſſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red that hauing repoſed my confidence in thy grace which is purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for mee in Chriſt, I ſhall, in my neceſſitie, find thy fauorable hand, by thy vertue to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all the enemies of my peace. But eſpecially graunt, O Lord, that I may attaine to this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:24771:107"/>of true wiſedome, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to bee content with thy will, the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne and iuſt cauſe of all things; namely, in that it pleaſeth thee, that the liuery of thy houſhold ſhould conſiſt in carying their croſſe after thy ſon, to the end, that I ſhould neuer but be ſeaſoned to drinke the wholeſome myrrhe which purgeth the ſoule from the luſts of the fleſh, and repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the ſame with the deſires of eternall life. Alſo that I learn in what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:24771:107"/>my eſtate, chere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to ſubmit my ſelfe to the conduct of thy prouidence, as beeing wel aſſured, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer I ſuffer, all the croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of my life ſhalbe vnto me ſo many bleſſings &amp; helpes from thee my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to make me goe the right way into thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and increaſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me the price of glory in the ſame. For it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true, that euery one ſhall freely receiue his reward according to the burthen that hee hath
<pb facs="tcp:24771:108"/>borne here below. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="prayer">
               <head>The ſixteenth Prayer, For obtaining the Vertue of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Al things written, are for our learning, that we, through patience and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the ſcriptures, might haue hope, patient in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, perſeuering in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Rom. 4. &amp; 12.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:108"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> GOD of pacience, and of all conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the iuſt diſpencer both of cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and benefits, and that all to one end, euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more happie to thoſe whom thou loueſt in thy eternall ſonne, our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, as there is nothing in thy worde, but ſerueth to our lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and to the guiding of our temporall life, as a meanes to obtaine the poſſeſſion of heauenly
<pb facs="tcp:24771:109"/>ioyes: ſo doeth it prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally inſiſt in this, to lift vp our heartes to an earneſt meditation, and firme expectation of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life, ſtanding vs in ſteede, in regard of the ſame, among the thorns of this worlde, to the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of a conſtant pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming vs by holie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations, to the ende, that hauing doone thy will, O Lorde, we may reape thy promiſe. This vertue therefore is the firme piller of our hope,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:109"/>and which teacheth vs, not to loue the things of the earth, as any felicity, but conſtantlie to looke vp into heauen, where our peace and ioy dooth remaine. But becauſe the effect of ſo holy a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doeth far ſurmount our owne forces. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, (my God) to graunt me this true pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the faithfull, which is ſo neceſſary for me, namely with a meek and moderate heart, to beare all aduerſitie, alſo that I may learn to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:24771:110"/>the pride of my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which otherwiſe is exceſſiue, and not to be tamed, that ſo I may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and knowe howe to contemne the vanitie of the fleſh his reaſoning, which toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the luſts therof is with ſweete and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thinges nouriſhed vnto death: and that contrariwiſe I may affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate, and ſtrengthen my ſelfe with goodlie meditations of the ſpirit, which ſuſtaine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with hard and
<pb facs="tcp:24771:110"/>ſharpe things, to a holie and heauenly life. That going forwarde, I may reioyce and take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in theſe ſacred ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: That affliction in the houſe of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, is a ſecret mercie which thou giueſt him, as proſperitie with the wicked is a hidden in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation of thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: That the preſent ſorrow of thy Children, is vnto them the watch of ſome future ioy at hand, and that at all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentures, the laſt of their
<pb facs="tcp:24771:111"/>moſt painefull dayes, is the firſt of their eternall reſt, in the ſecond life. If therfore I beare any ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or other miſerie in my fleſh, let it bee borne with patience, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very wel, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of ſinne is death, and the ſorrows and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemperatures of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die are the heraults, and neceſſary fore-runners, euen acceptable to all true faithfull people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they call and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to departe from labour to reſt, from
<pb facs="tcp:24771:111"/>a mortall eſtate, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie of life. If I haue but fewe of theſe goods and vaine honors of the world, that doe ſo vex worldly men, I doe liue in the greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, not ſubiect to their enuie, but taking com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the true and only goods of the ſoule, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, O Lord, thou art the liberall giuer, as alſo of grace, to thoſe that are thine, becauſe thou art their Father. O Lorde our Redeemer, if I looſe ſome of my friends, euen
<pb facs="tcp:24771:112"/>of thoſe that are very neere me; yet can I take it peaceably, becauſe their felicitie is haſtened, in that they departe in Chriſt, and that I can looſe, neither thee, nor the conſolation of thy ſpirit, for that I ſhal ſoon after follow them into heauen, whereby I ſhall therefore bee the rather mooued to giue thee thankes for the time that thy goodneſſe hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen mee to enioy their preſence to the comfort of my life, and not as it
<pb facs="tcp:24771:112"/>were by a certaine kinde of ingratitude towards, both thee and them, mourne for their ioy and felicitie. In all other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and griefes that ſhould leſſe trouble vs, giue me grace, my Lord, that I be not mooued to bitterneſſe or anger, but that with a quiet minde, I may beare al, and tread vnder feete the thornes of my life, as being aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the end, to finde both the coſts, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. To the ſame end alſo touch my heart ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
<pb facs="tcp:24771:113"/>with the feeling of thy benefits; namely, of thoſe which thou haſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally granted vs, for the neceſſities of this life, leſt, as an ingrateful wretch I ſhould forget them, after the maner of carnall men that are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer content with thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, but doe enioy them without any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement, and which is more, are ready to complain if they haue not all their vanities at a wiſh: yea which is worſt of all, when they haue
<pb facs="tcp:24771:113"/>often eaten at the table of thy Sonne, doe lift vp their heele againſt him, wherein they are worſe then beaſts, that doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thoſe that feede and dreſſe them, and doe humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their preſence. O moſt mightie GOD, deliuer mee from the counſell of theſe wicked ones and hypocrites, and let mee not ſit vpon the ſeate of theſe ſcorners, with whom godlineſſe is folly, and the equitie of thy law but a ſporte.
<pb facs="tcp:24771:114"/>But whether I walke, or ſtand ſtil, whether I do, or ſuffer, grant, O Lord, that I may alwaies walke as in thy preſence, to the glory of thy holy name, and that my ſoule may take counſaile, and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whilſt in all pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence I waite for my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance from all paine, and the perfection of my felicity, at my departure from this carnall habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when according to thy promiſe I ſhall be receiued into thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:114"/>in the company of the Angels &amp; Saints, there to behold thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eternally. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="prayer">
               <head>The ſeuenteenth Praier, For the good v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of mans life.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Thus ſayeth the Lord, let not the wiſeman boaſt of his wiſedome, neither the ſtrong man of his ſtrength, neither the rich man of his riches: but let him that
<pb facs="tcp:24771:115"/>boasteth, doe it becauſe hee hath vnderstanding, and knoweth me, that I am the Lorde who ſhewe mercie, iudgement and iustice vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ieremie. 9.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, great &amp; wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in thy works, thou in thy wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome haſt made and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained them all; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the heauens, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeaking do declare thy glory, and the earth is full of thy riches. But
<pb facs="tcp:24771:115"/>eſpecially vppon man haſt thou powred forth thy moſt aboundaunt treaſures, in that thou haſt created him to thy likeneſſe, excellent in all good things, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed him the poſſeſſer of the world, Lord of all other creatures, the mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of thy wiſedome, the beames of thy light, the pattern of thy goodnes, and the moſt noble in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of thy name: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haſt thou endued man with an immortal
<pb facs="tcp:24771:116"/>ſpirit, capable of reaſon, to the end, I ſay, that in beholding here beneath the exquiſite workes of thy handes, and vſing them without interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hee might knowe, loue, feare, and honour thee as his father and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor; Yea cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee for euer, vſing his lif according to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall end thereof. True it is, that by originall ſinne wee are all fallen from the moſt ſingular qualities, neceſſarie for the holding of our right
<pb facs="tcp:24771:116"/>courſe to ſo great felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: Yet haue we not ſo put them off as to reſt altogether naked, for all that is re-eſtabliſhed in vs, and in a farre better condition, by thy grace in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt who cloatheth vs anewe with the newe man in a quickening ſpirite, and furniſheth vs with his light, to the end, that in the ſerious meditation of thy viſible workes, &amp; in the right vſe of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites which wee taſte therin, we might appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend
<pb facs="tcp:24771:117"/>the celeſtial inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thee the authour and perſection of all that is. That is, how the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens appearing to our eyes, and the greatneſſe and the beautie, and the motions therof in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorts, ſo wel ordered, &amp; ſo profitable, do make vs, with our inteligence, to penetrate euen vnto thee, the admirable cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of all things; and in the excellencie of the ſame, to meditate vpon the height and depth of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:117"/>thy excellency, to the end, to ſing vnto thee, Pſalms of thankſgiuing, and in the ſelfe ſame, to finde reſt and comforte for our ſouls. Alſo wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the ſunne lighteth and warmeth vs, the day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth vs, the aire quik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vs, the earth fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs, the water moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth vs, and the night miniſters to vs reſt from our labours: and which is more (O Father of all the world) whereas thou maintaineſt orders and gouernments, that thou
<pb facs="tcp:24771:118"/>pulleſt down the prowd, and exalteſt the humble, that thou extendeſt thy puniſhments vppon the earth, and the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof, that thou viſiteſt them with mercy exerciſing thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vpon ſmall fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, as well as vpon great Monarchies, (according as there is nothing in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that taketh place, more or leſſe, in reſpect of thy infinite glory:) ſurely in all theſe things, O inuiſible GOD, thou makeſt thy ſelfe to bee
<pb facs="tcp:24771:118"/>ſeene, and giueſt vs cauſe to ſing to thy name, with a moſt excellent induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to paſſe ouer our life ſoberly. But if wee turne vnto our ſelues to conſider our owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, eſpecially the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the ſoule, and the reaſon thereof, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth the body, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth diuerſe vertues to all the ſenſes, and that we repreſent to our ſelues the admirable coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the immortall eſſence with the mortall: Indeed ruminating theſe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:119"/>workes of thy hands, and vnable to comprehend the cauſes and ſecrets of the ſame, wee yeeld our ſelues ouercome, that we may preach forth the victory of thy ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne wiſedome, and ſay with the Prophet (Thy knowledge is too maruelous for vs, and ſo high, that we cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch thereto.) But if proceeding beyond this Booke of Nature, wee come to reade in the Booke of the Lambe ſlaine for our ranſome,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:119"/>and to ſee and meditate vpon the husbandrie of thy ſheepefold, and the aboundance of celeſtiall bleſſings in the ſame, O Lord what height and depth of wiſedome, of charitie, of mercy of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, is in the ſame? O the greatneſſe of ioy and peace to the illuminate hearts, that can penetrate into all theſe diuine my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, when we come to thy church to learne thy law, to heare the goſpel, to worſhip and call vpon thee, and to ſound forth
<pb facs="tcp:24771:120"/>thy praiſe, wee are as it were in the ſanctuary of thy kingdome, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy face among the Angels to contemplate and celebrate thy glory.</p>
               <p>Alſo when wee doe communicate in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſignes of thy coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, we ſee, wee touch, we taſte with our eyes, with our hands, &amp; with the pallat of our ſoules the water of waſhing &amp; regeneration, and the bread of life (the foode of the ſanctified ſpirits) whereof wee liue, and
<pb facs="tcp:24771:120"/>ſhal liue for euer bleſſed. Beſides (O heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) it pleaſeth thee to giue vs heere belowe in the following of our courſe, a conuenient lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to meditate vppon the moſt wonderfull ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of thy ſpirite in vs, the ſingular woorke of our new birth, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of our faith, the fruites of our loue, the feeling of our peace in the hope of our ſaluation to come, when wee ſhal, by Chriſt, be wholly v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited vnto thee alone. I
<pb facs="tcp:24771:121"/>beſeech thee therefore, my GOD, to giue mee grace in theſe godly and ſpirituall conſiderations, to acknowlege thy great benignitie in the gift and vſe of this humane life, and to know how I am to cheriſh and nouriſh the ſame, becauſe it is vnto vs as a treaſure, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in al excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, riches, and prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiues, which it hath pleaſed thee to impart to our nature, the Image of thy glory. So that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining conſtant in my
<pb facs="tcp:24771:121"/>vocation, in the pathes of thy Kingdome, and free from the cares of the world, and all the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties therof, I may ſo loue this life, that it may bee wholy deare vnto me, onely to know, worſhip, and ſerue thee, and my neighbours, according to the place whereto thou doſt call mee; and carefully to meditate to the ſame end, how thou doeſt alwayes miniſter iuſtice, iudgement, and mercy, whereby I may learne to liue content in
<pb facs="tcp:24771:122"/>thee onely, and of thy goods, vſing the ſame with acknowledgement and alwayes reioycing in well doing, alwayes aſſured that thus fighting a good fight, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the faith, I ſhal ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the crowne of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall righteouſneſſe in the kingdome of glory. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="prayer">
               <head>The eighteenth Prayer, Vpon temporall death.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:122"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Our life is but a vapour which appeareth but for a while, and then vaniſheth away. For the reward of ſinne is death, and the ſting thereof is ſinne. But thanks be to God, who hath giuen vs victory, through our Lord Ieſus Christ.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Rom. 6 1. Cor. 15.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> eternal god, with whom a thouſand yeares are as one day, &amp; one day as a thouſand
<pb facs="tcp:24771:123"/>yeres, and whoſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo diuerſe, are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, iuſt, and incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible. Where is the man ſo gallant or prowd, who thinking vpon the vanitie and ſhortneſſe of his life, doeth not eaſily aſſwage his pride and preſumption, euen to the end that hee extend not his temporall cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations too farre, but keepe them bounded within the limits of thy law, and referre the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent to the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of thy will?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:123"/>
               <p>The vertue of our fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt daies is but affliction of minde, and miſerie of our fleſh, we fall as by a guſhing of waters, wee paſſe away as a dreame, or a ſmoake, our eares doe conſume like graſſe, that withereth from night vnto morning, and the longeſt time of our courſe, (whereof ſleepe nibleth awaie a good part) is but three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and tenne yeares, or foure-ſcore for the ſtrongeſt bodies, whileſt in euerie moment of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:124"/>life, the neareſt and ſinalleſt daunger that threatneth vs, ſeemeth to be death, which as our ſhadow, followeth vs at the heeles, and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at our goodly deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, vntill ſhe hath ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them in the winde, &amp; brought vs into aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. But which is worſe, where is the man, ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perfect, that doth not tremble and quake, if there bee repreſented vnto him, (O Lord) the tribunall ſeate of thy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne iuſtice, where
<pb facs="tcp:24771:124"/>we all, after death, muſt appeare? Thy indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt ſinners is manifeſt (and there is none righteous) thy ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance is readie againſt rebellion (whereof wee bee all guiltie) which doth alſo cauſe, that death is vnto vs, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as a temporall ending as concerning the fleſh, (whereat nature is moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and abaſhed,) but alſo an interior feeling of the curſe fallen vppon ſinne, yea euen an entry into eternall death, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:125"/>there be for vs with thee our Father, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption in our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt. I beſeech thee therfore, my God, to giue mee grace to knowe, how to meditate euerie day of my life vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ſentence of the holy ghoſt. (That it is decreed that al men ſhal die once, and after that ſhall the iudgement fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe,) to the ende that while I creepe vppe and downe in this earthlie myre, I ſuffer not my ſelfe to be deceiued with
<pb facs="tcp:24771:125"/>the deceiptfull baites of the pleaſures of this worlde, neyther with the allurements of the diuell, who ſtill ſeeketh by his ſuttleties to race out of our hearts the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of death, ſo for to detaine vs in the thoughts of vanitie, and to entangle vs in the ſnares of our Iuſts. Grant me rather (O Lord) to knowe the vileneſſe and bitterneſſe of this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable life, to the end that withdrawing my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from mortall things,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:126"/>I may bee able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and ſtay my ſelfe in things ſtedfaſt and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. And alſo that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the remembrance of death, may daily be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee, as a trumpet to waken and call mee, to the purſuite of my life, in the path of thy truth, &amp; to kindle in mee a holie deſire, ſoone to departe out of the world, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the longer a man ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iournes, the more is hee loaden with infernall Marchandize (which is the filthines of ſinne)
<pb facs="tcp:24771:126"/>and the more he cutteth him ſelfe off from that portion of ſoueraign fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie which is in the life to come. Truely he that hath moſt yeares hath moſt iniquitie, and hee that croucheth moſt in the mire of the world, rotteth moſt. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the Children of darkeneſſe, the vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the fleſh is a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant habitation: But to the children of light, to the immortall ſpirites, to the regenerate heartes, heauen is much more
<pb facs="tcp:24771:127"/>deſiderable. Grant ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, my God, that as I dayly grow towards my end, ſo I may liue the more cheerefully, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in thy ſchoole, to preferre thy eternal life, before the light of the Sunne, the glory of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, before the vanitie of the earth, the glorious habitation in paradice, before the painefull tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults of the worlde, the ſocietie of Angells, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fellowſhippe of mortall men, the onelie bleſſed and permanent
<pb facs="tcp:24771:127"/>life, before the paſſing ſhaddowe of this life, which is fruitfull in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes, ryotes, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, the triumph be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the combat, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent poſſeſſion of ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne good, before the hope of enioying: and that attending this hauen of health, I may know how to prepare my ſelfe by continuall meditation in theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Chriſtian conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, that happy are they that die in the Lord for they reſt from their
<pb facs="tcp:24771:128"/>labors: That death is to them no death, but a ſleepe, in regard of their bodies, then freed from the miſeries of life: and that, as for the ſoule, which findeth it ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of ſinne, it is to her a change to a better life: That this death is to all faithfull, the time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the garlands for their race, &amp; the crowns of their labours. That to them ſhee is an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table iſſue of a laborious trauell, their deliuerie
<pb facs="tcp:24771:128"/>from all terror and feare, and the ſtedfaſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of their voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to felicitie: which made the Apoſtle to ſay, (Alas! wretched man that I am, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me from this bodie of death? I deſire to bee diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt) howbeit if not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie of my fleſh, the fearefull Image of death trouble me in the ſtraites of my departure, If the world that doth alwayes too much bewitch vs,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:129"/>maketh my thoughts then bowe to his will: If Sathan pitcheth his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, and ſnares, and vpon the remembrance of my ſinnes, ſetteth hell before my face: moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, if my owne pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations keepe me from apprehending thy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall conſolations, in ſuch moſt neceſſarie extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, vouchſafe (my good God and father) in theſe anguiſhes, to approach vnto me, to ſaue me from the running and ſwift ſtreame of ſuch brookes,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:129"/>that they may not carrie meaway to perdition, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate my thoughts with thy ſpirite, waken my ſoule out of the ſleep of death, renew my hart by the vertue of thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and put into my hands, the ſtaffe of thy aſſured conduct, to bring mee out from the laborinth of this ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful paſſage, cauſing me, with the eyes of my faith, to behold my righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes vpon the croſſe of my Sauiour, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my debts in
<pb facs="tcp:24771:130"/>his ſacrifice, my victorie in his combats, my life in his death, my glorie and ioy in his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that ſo repleniſhed with peace, I may cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reſigne my bodie to the earth, as aſſured that it ſhall riſe againe, and my ſoule to heauen, with theſe laſt words of Chriſt, [Into thy hands, O Father, I commit my ſpirit.] So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:130"/>
               <head>The nineteenth Prayer, For heauenly life.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Hee that heareth my worde, and beleeueth in him that ſent me, hath life euerlasting, and I wil raiſe him again at the latter day. Father, concerning thoſe whome thou haſt giuen me my deſire is, that they may be where I am, that they may be with me to beholde my glory.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Iohn. 5. &amp;. 6. &amp;. 17.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:131"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Soueraign Father of al thinges, &amp; by a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge, Father of the children whome it hath pleaſed thee to adopt in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to be coheires with him in the celeſtiall life, I learne in thy word, that this inheritance &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate is acontempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the glory of this great Sauiour of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, in an vnſpeakeable
<pb facs="tcp:24771:131"/>beatitude, onely worthy to be loued, and to bee ſought inceſſantly night and day, with the lamp of thy trueth. Which is to ſee him as he is (true God, and true Man) and perfectlie to enioie his preſence with commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating of all his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to be in the ioy of his Lord, as a loyall ſeruant, and to beholde him face to face in his diuine eſſence, one with the father, and with the holy ghoſt, one onelie God in ſoueraigne Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie
<pb facs="tcp:24771:132"/>which is to be vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and conioyned with him, and by him; vnto thee, O eternall GOD, who art all light and life, of the ſoule at her depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of her earthly habitation, afterward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſted with it fleſh in that great day of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious comming of the ſame Chriſt, when hee ſhall wholy render vppe vnto thee the kingdome of thy grace, that thou maiſt be all in all: To be briefe, (which is both in body and ſoule) to be
<pb facs="tcp:24771:132"/>in him, and to liue of his glory. And this alſo is the eternall life, a life ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, in loue, in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, in reſt, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, in beautie, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, in ioy, felicitie, and peace, a life wherin the Angels and Saintes inceſſantly do ſound out and celebrate, O Lord, thy great name, in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and rauiſhing melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, repleniſhed both with a deſire, and a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the celeſtiall bread (Ieſus Chriſt God
<pb facs="tcp:24771:133"/>&amp; man) without this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire breeding any griefe, or this fulneſſe any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation. In ſumme, a life, which by the full view that wee ſhall haue of thy eternall deitie (O almightie GOD) ſhall make vs knowe thee, as thou haſt knowne vs, and as thou art in Trinitie of perſons (Father, Word, Spirit,) and in vnitie of eſſence: likewiſe to loue thee according to the excellency of thy nature with our whole heartes and thoughts, and our
<pb facs="tcp:24771:133"/>whole ſtrength, and might, and in this loue to obtaine our perfect &amp; full contentment. To this heauenlie life, O Lord, my ſoule directeth her flight, this is the marke that ſhee aymeth at, the end whereto ſhee tendeth, and the reward that ſhe, by thy grace, promiſeth her ſelfe, for ſeeking after thy welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Sonne, in whome it pleaſeth thee to be my God and my Father. Oh! I ſhall indeede goe and liue in this holy and
<pb facs="tcp:24771:134"/>ſacred place of the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of thy glorie, and there ſhall contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate that which neuer eye ſawe vnder the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, neyther eare hath heard, nor heart com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, of the ſolide Riches whiche thou dooſt keepe from all eternitie for thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>I ſhall ſee, I ſay, theſe diuine wonders in thy ſanctuary, in thy light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceſſible for all fleſh, knowing in the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy countenance
<pb facs="tcp:24771:134"/>thy infinite power [O Father] thy incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible wiſedome (O Sonne) and thy incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable vertue (O Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghoſt) one onely true God. A knowledge ſo ſingular and pretious, that therein reſteth all the felicitie of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and ſaints, their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly plentiful reward, their ſcepter, the diademe of their glory, and the full and perpetuall ioy that couereth their heads as with a crowne of victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in a peace durable for
<pb facs="tcp:24771:135"/>euer. I beſeech thee ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O Lord, to giue mee grace, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing my affection more and more from the darke cloyſters of the earth, ſprinckled with teares, I may lift vp my deſires to the lightſome habitation of thy deitie, where the treaſures and incomparable ioyes of thy paradiſe do remaine in an eternall life. So that I may finiſhe my courſe in an earneſt and perpetuall meditation of this angelical and diuine
<pb facs="tcp:24771:135"/>being, and comforting my ſelf inceſſantly night and day, in that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is made vnto mee through my ſauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to the end, that in my laſt hower (come out of my miſery and entered into my fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie) I may with a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py flight goe take my reſt aboue in thy peace, O my God, which ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounteth all vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and for to ſing Pſalmes of thankſgiuing vnto thee without end. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:136"/>
               <head>The twentieth Praier, Vpon eternall death.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Of thoſe that ſleepe in the duſt of the earth, ſome ſhall awake to euerlaſting life, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to rebuke and ſhame without end. Their worme ſhall not die; and their fire ſhall not be quenched: there ſhalbe weeping &amp; gnaſhing of teethe.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Dan. 12. Eſay. 66. Mat. 15.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:136"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmighty god, for whoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie all nations are created. Thou which art the mightie and the faithfull God, keeping thy coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and free mercy with a thouſand genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thoſe that loue thee, and obey thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, &amp; which giueſt againe the very ſame vnto thoſe that hate thee, and rebell againſt thee with euery of them euen to their face, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:137"/>will is the iuſt and ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne cauſe of all that is done in heauen, and in earth, whoſe counſailes are vnſearchable, and iudgements moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and admirable. O Father and gouernor of all things, thou haſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from the beginning of thy vnſpeakable good neſſe framed man, and reclothed him with ſuch an excellency, as did ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently preach forth the infinite power of thy hand, which had crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him ſuch a one. I wil
<pb facs="tcp:24771:137"/>not, neither can I aſcend higher then thy word teacheth me, to enquire wherefore thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not ſo eſtabliſh the bleſſed being of this the greateſt and chiefeſt of thy viſible workes, that he might not fall, I haue matter enough to occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py the ſtrength of my ſoule, to meditate vpon, to haue in deteſtation, yea euen before thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie to accuſe the pride of our nature, which thought not it ſelfe in honor ſufficient, vnleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:138"/>it were equall with thy deitie, freeing it ſelfe from all feare, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto thee, and by that raſh ingratitude caſt himſelfe headlong from innocency into ſinne, from life into temporall and eternall death. To thee, O Lord, belongeth righteouſneſſe, and to man confuſion &amp; ſhame, and thou, after thy good pleaſure, ſheweſt mercy to whom thou wilt ſhew mercy. The vaine Philoſophie, and fooliſh curioſitie, which is not
<pb facs="tcp:24771:138"/>content with the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of Chriſtian faith, retained within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of thy ſacred Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, ſhal make much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry about this fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> to the end (if ſhe could) to penetrate into thy ſecret counſaile, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the creation and end of thy workes; yea euen in that which tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the election and reprobation of mankind ſhee dareth in this bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit to dicourſe of thy infinite iuſtice, &amp; the argument of thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible
<pb facs="tcp:24771:139"/>glory, meaſuring both the one and the other, with her terreſtiall conceits, for to declare in her imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thy grace to the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and thy iudgement againſt the reprobate, daring to pleade their cauſe, as alſo ſhe will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue of their eſtate after this life, and of the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But thy children, O heauenly Father, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by thy doctrine through the light of thy ſpirit, will in their hearts
<pb facs="tcp:24771:139"/>humblie reuerence thy decrees, which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes iuſt, euen in the firſt condemnation of al mankinde, and will be content to magnifie thy goodneſſe, for the grace that it hath pleaſed thee to beſtow vpon them in Ieſus Chriſt, adopting them by him of thy free mercy into thy family. For they haue learned in thy ſchoole that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceſſible brightneſſe of thy iudgements, dazleth the beſt ſighted mindes and ſpirits: yea waſteth
<pb facs="tcp:24771:140"/>and conſumeth them when they preſume to approach to enquire the ſecret cauſes. This doe I know, (neither will I know any more) that all things doe worke for the beſt in thy elect, becauſe that hauing known them before all ages, thou haſt alſo predeſtinated them to be made conformable to the image of thy Son, called and iuſtified them to be glorified. The veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of wrath prepared to perdition, do feele none of theſe free mercies and
<pb facs="tcp:24771:140"/>celeſtiall riches, whereof it comes, that when they thinke vpon death, they ſee nothing but feareful, horrible, damnable, all intollerable paine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diminution or end: an infernall diueliſh, and endleſſe torment, a gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of teeth, with blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy and diſpaire, a perpetuall diſquiet both in body and ſoule, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity to their woe and damnation; and which is worſe, a moſt merciful God, whom they ſhall know to be in heauen,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:141"/>and yet not to bee their God, but their aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, &amp; ſoueraigne Iudge, to be as ſeuere and rigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to them, as he ſhall be gentle and fauorable to his children. This is in ſumme, all that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate may expect or hope for in death. This alſo maketh, that when they find they are vtterly deſtitute of the pledge of their fredome, which thy elect (O Lord) doe carry with them, in this ſinne of nature (namely faith in Chriſt) dead for
<pb facs="tcp:24771:141"/>their ſinnes, and riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for their righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; theſe miſerable men departe this their earthly habitation, with great griefe and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, vſually at the how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of death caſting forth many woeful ſobbes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible fore-runners of their miſery at hand: As in truth they want no more thereof but the proofe that they are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to make, of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall torments with the diuells in the burning lake of fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:142"/>which is neuer quenched, giuen to the ſoule preſently vpon the temporall death, and to both body and ſoule in the day of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all fleſh, I ſay in the ſecond &amp; eternall death, a death which continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth without dying, and without conſuming, or deſtroying, that which it makes to languiſh for, euer in a furnace, always burning, deuouring and conſuming: amongeſt which vnſpeakeable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (yea ſuch as mans
<pb facs="tcp:24771:142"/>thought is not able to conceiue) this paine is not the leaſt to the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (but rather an other cruell death) that they neuer haue any motion of the ſpirit to repent or conuert vnto thee the onely and true God. I beſeech thee therefore, O Lord, that as thou haſt giuen me grace to belieue that by thy grace I am made a veſſell of mercy, I may liue in the life of the righteous, ſanctified by the ſpirit of Chriſt, to depart happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:24771:143"/>in him, and ſo to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend vnto thee into thy new <hi>Sion,</hi> and there to receiue the price of the victorious crown, which this great Sauior of the elect hath purchaſed for the perfection of their glory. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="prayer">
               <head>The one and twentieth Prayer. For the Morning,</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:143"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>O Lord, euen in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning heare my voice: Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in the morning will I direct my praier vnto thee, and will looke vp. O Lord I crie vnto thee, and earlie ſhall my praier come before thee. Let my helpe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning be in the name of god (Father, Sonne and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li-ghoſt) who hath made heauen and earth.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 5. &amp; 88.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord my God eternal and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, to whom I owe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:144"/>all glory and obedience, I doe humbly proſtrate my ſelfe before thy face, and lift vp my heart and voice to thee my Father which art in heauen, to ſanctifie thy name, to craue thy mercy, and to giue thee thankes for thy benefits. I acknowledge of thy prouidence and benignitie, that hauing paſſed this night vnder thy gard and protection, I may yet ſee the light of the day, &amp; in the workes of thy hands, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate the greatneſſe of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:144"/>thy power, and here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low enioy thoſe tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall benefites that thou powreſt plentifully or largely vppon thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>But becauſe of thy vnmeaſurable bountie, thou makeſt earthlie things common to all men, and that the effects of the Sonne doe ſtand vs no ſteede but for the life of the bodie, I bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee (merciful Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) more and more to raiſe vpon my heart thy eternall light (our Lord
<pb facs="tcp:24771:145"/>Ieſus Chriſt) and by the vertue of thy ſpirit, ſo to ſcatter the darkeneſſe of my vnderſtanding, and to breake the hardneſſe of my heart, that ſo farre as it may ſuffize for my ſaluation, I may appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the glorie of thy Kingdome, and the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of chriſtian faith, together with the dutie of my calling, that I may conſtantly walke in the ſame, in a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and as before thee, the ſearcher of our harts with all my thoughtes
<pb facs="tcp:24771:145"/>worſhipping and louing thee in ſpirit and trueth according to thy word: louing alſo, in thee, my neighboures as my ſelfe, to pleaſure them ſo farre forth as I may, by thy grace: but becauſe my ignorance and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, doe carrie mee far from ſuch wiſdome, and fulfilling of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, beeing a poore ſinner, weake in faith, ſlowe in hope, colde in charitie, and polluted with many offences that make mee worthie of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:146"/>death and of hell. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, my God, in thy fatherly loue to bear with theſe my defects, and to forgiue mee my treſpaſſes, in the name of thy Sonne our Mediator and Sauiour, accepting his ſacrifice as a full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for my ſinnes, and imputing vnto mee his righteouſneſſe, to life euerlaſting.</p>
               <p>Yea and to the ſame end alſo, vouchſafe to encreaſe in my ſoule the giftes of thy Spirite, ſo as I may from better to
<pb facs="tcp:24771:146"/>better, proſecute my life in the path of thine elect, being through thy pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er freed from the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Diuell, the worlde, and my owne fleſh, and by thy bleſſing preſerued from the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and miſeries of this poore life, alwayes not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding content with whatſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe thee to beſtow on me.</p>
               <p>Sith thou art my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I cannot but expect a happy end of all my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates hauing alredy rece<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:24771:147"/>of thy mercy, the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured pledge of ſaluation (forgiueneſſe of ſinnes) But Lord, graunt eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally that this thy grace in Ieſus Chriſt, may be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee a comforte, and light all the dayes of my life, eſpeciallie in the darkeneſſe of my death, to retaine and holde me faſt in the hope of my ſaluation, that with a liuelie faith at my laſt gaſpe I may ſpeake theſe words of my Sauior vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the croſſe, (Into thy handes, (O Father) I
<pb facs="tcp:24771:147"/>commend my ſpirite,) whereby my ſoule alſo inwardly may heare the ſame Chriſt ſaying vnto mee, as vnto the poore penitent theefe (Sonne, reioyce, this day thou ſhalt be with me in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice) ſo that full of peace, by the effects of thy ſpirit, I may cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully leaue my body to the earth, aſſured of the reſurrection, and that my ſoule may, by the angels, be guided to the reſt of the bleſſed, and vouchſafe, O Lord, to do
<pb facs="tcp:24771:148"/>the like fauor to all men, euen as I craue theſe thinges, in the prayer which thy Sonne hath taught me. <hi>[Our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which art in heauen, hallowed be thy name. Thy Kingdome come. Thy will be done, in earth as it is in heauen. Giue vs this daie our dayly bread, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs our treſpaſſes, as wee forgiue them that treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe againſt vs. And leade vs not into temptation, but deliuer vs from euill. For thine is the Kingdome, the power and the glory, world
<pb facs="tcp:24771:148"/>without end.</hi> Amen. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (my God) encreaſe in me, faith working e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie good worke, and giue me grace conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to perſeuere, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to make confeſſion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to my laſt gaſpe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>[I beleeue in God the father almightie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of heauen and earth. And in Ieſus Christ his only Sonne our Lord, who was conceiued by the holie Ghost, borne of the Virgin</hi> Marie, <hi>ſuffered vnder</hi> Ponce Pilate, <hi>was crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, dead and buried, hee
<pb facs="tcp:24771:149"/>deſcended into hell, the third day hee roſe againe, from the dead: he aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth at the right hand of God the Father almightie. From thence hee ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the dead. I beleeue in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-Ghost, the holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church. The commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints, the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes. The reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the fleſh, and the life euerlasting.]</hi> This is my faith O Lord, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I will liue and die, as alſo in the obſeruation
<pb facs="tcp:24771:149"/>of thy holy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, comprized in theſe two <hi>(That wee loue thee with all our hart, with all our ſoule, with all our ſtrength, and with all our thoughtes, and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours as our ſelues.</hi> Thus thy grace, O my God and Father, be with me, and thy bleſſing vpon all the workes of my hands. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:150"/>
               <head>The two and twentieth Prayer. Among the Family.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>At noone, at night, &amp; in the morning will I crie vnto God, and the Eternal ſhall deliuer me. I wil make a noiſe, and hee ſhall heare my voyce (ſaide <hi>Dauid</hi>) and <hi>Daniel</hi> kneeled down three times a day in his houſe, prayed vnto, and magnified his God.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 55. &amp; 18. Dan. 6.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:150"/>
               <head>Our help and beginning be in the name of God.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> LORD our GOD, and our Father, onelie great in glorie, &amp; of infinit power. It hath pleaſed thee ſo far forth to honour men (poore Wormes of the Earth) that they may in ful con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fidence, in thy loue and bountie, preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues before thy face, to magnifie thy name: to
<pb facs="tcp:24771:151"/>talke of thy beneficence, and to craue thy mercy. Wee humblie beſeech thee therfore by thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to diſpoſe of our ſouls, our hearts, and our lips to glorifie thee, and ſo to call vppon thee, that our vowes may be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto thee, and our prayers heard, wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſelues, in thy preſence, to bee ſo great ſinners, that our vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe will not ſuffer vs to look vp vnto heauen, without feare that thou ſhouldeſt, in thy iuſt
<pb facs="tcp:24771:151"/>wrath thunder vpon vs: neither can wee caſt our eyes vpon the earth, but we ſhall ſee as it were hel open for the reward of our wickedneſſe: for we are, not only as the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Adam,</hi> concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and borne in ſinne, worthy of thy curſe, but alſo, by our owne faults, luſts, vncleaneneſſe, bad thoughtes, and wicked works, whereinto throgh our corruption and frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wee doe daily fall, which alſo in our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are ſo many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb facs="tcp:24771:152"/>to condemne vs, and as it were heraultes that doe denounce vnto vs death and hel: But (O Lord) thy mercies do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely exceede our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and thy eternall compaſſions, are vppon ſinners that conuert and turne vnto thee. Thou art that pittifull Father, that gladly receiued his prodigall and vnthriftie Son. That louing ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard that carefully ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the loſt ſheepe; that charitable phiſition, that freely commeth to the
<pb facs="tcp:24771:152"/>ſicke to cure them. Wee therefore the children of thy loue, the ſheepe of thy folde, and the poore in ſpirit, doe moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech thee in the name of thy welbeloued Sonne our mediator Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to vouchſafe to take away all our cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities in pardoning our ſinnes, becauſe thou haſt giuen vs this great Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the worlde, to the end, that whoſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting. We are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
<pb facs="tcp:24771:153"/>in his name, wee haue receiued his goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: and he giueth vs his body in thy church for ſpirituall foode, that we may liue in him, and of him for euer bleſſed. Giue vs grace therefore, O our God, with a true and liuely faith, vphelde by hope, and doing eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good worke, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, to the glorie of thy name, and the peace of our ſoules, theſe great benefits that are purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for vs, in the death and paſſion of the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:24771:153"/>our redeemer, that wee may inceſſantly yeelde prayſings vnto thee, and liue in holineſſe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy worde. For the performance hereof vouchſafe to encreaſe the giftes of thy ſpirit in our hearts, whereby the deſires of the fleſh, and vanities of the worlde, may bee mortified, and the pure fire of thy loue ſo kindled, that we may loue, honour and ſerue thee, with all our ſoules, with all our ſtrengths, and with al our mindes,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:154"/>and louing our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours as our ſelues, to pleaſure them in all due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of loue to our pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Strengthen vs like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with thy vertue, O almightie God, againſt the temptations and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of Sathan, deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vs victoriouſly, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing vs alſo from ſuch dangers and miſeries, as euery where follow vs at the heeles in this life: and aboue all, giuing vs grace, in whatſoeuer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate wee be, ſtill to be content with thy will,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:154"/>which can neuer be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than good and iuſt, and to vs profitable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee are of the number of thy children. So let thy peace be in vs, and vpon all the workes of our handes, that wee may happily paſſe the reſt of our dayes, walke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euery of vs in his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, in the duty of our vocation, in a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as before thy face, to whom nothing is hid: and meditating di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, vpon the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and afflictions of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:155"/>this our life, that ſo wee may aduance thee, and finally end in the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of true chriſtians: whereby wee may prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally learne to deſire heauen, and patiently to take all humane croſſes, and whatſoeuer may ſeeme to vs moſt gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous to the fleſh, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all things ſhall turne to our good; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alwayes prouided, that conſtantly we perſeuere in thy ſeruice, for ſo ſhal wee liue and die with Chriſt, that we may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:24771:155"/>into his ioyes in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, there to behold his glory. Furthermore, howſoeuer vnworthie ſinners wee are, yet O Lord, in as much as thou haſt commanded vs to pray one for another, to the aduancement of thy Kingdome, wee pray to thee for all men, that it may pleaſe thee ſo to worke, that they who as yet haue not the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy holy goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, may, by the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, and the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of thy holy
<pb facs="tcp:24771:156"/>ſpirite, be brought to know thee the only and true GOD, and him whome thou haſt ſent, Ieſus Chriſt, to ſaue the Worlde. Alſo that they whom thou haſt already viſited with this grace, as our ſelues, may dayly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in thy ſpirituall bleſſings: So that alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether we may worſhip thee with hart &amp; mouth in one ſpirite, one faith, and one baptiſme. And ſith thou haſt alſo ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned gouernements and callings, that all people
<pb facs="tcp:24771:156"/>may be gouerned in the feare of thy name, and to common commoditie. We beſeech thee to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, guide and bleſſe our Queen, and all Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Magiſtrates and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, that haue the gouernement of thy ſword vpon earth, that euery of them raigning in godlineſſe and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, may employ their power which they hold from thee, to cauſe thee to be ſerued &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored, and to the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie, peace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:157"/>of their ſubiects, wholy ſubmitting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their people, to thy holy word. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the publiſhing of thy word in al places, vouchſafe more &amp; more with thy giftes to enrich the Paſtors and Doctors of thy Church, and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to raiſe vp more to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute in a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence their charge, to the edification and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy holy Temple, whereof, in generall (O Lorde) and of euerie faithfull, vouchſafe to
<pb facs="tcp:24771:157"/>ſhewe thy ſelfe the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty protector, to the confuſion of all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of the name of Chriſt, and of his holie Church.</p>
               <p>We alſo pray thee for all thoſe whom thou vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiteſt with tribulation, whether it be ſickeneſſe of body, or anguiſh of ſoule, that thou, O mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, vouchſafe to giue them comfort &amp; patience, to the bearing of their calamities, and deliueraunce from their afflictions. Asking all
<pb facs="tcp:24771:158"/>theſe things of thee in the name of thy Sonne our Mediatour, and as he hath taught vs to pray <hi>Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</hi> We alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech thee O Lord to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and confirme vs in the Catholike Faith of thy Church, to the end it may take liuely roote in our ſoules to fructifie, to all righteonſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and good workes: and that euen to our laſt gaſpe, we may make like confeſſion thereof, as we doe now both with hart
<pb facs="tcp:24771:158"/>and mouth. <hi>(I beleeue in God the Father Almighty, &amp;c.)</hi> And becauſe the faith of thy children, O Lord, is inſeperable from the obedience due to thy word, eſpecially in the tenne commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the law, and that thou doeſt ordaine, that wee ſhould haue them perpetually in our hearts and mouthes, to keepe them, and to teach them to our families, giue vs grace, to our pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers, to conforme our ſelues to the ſame, euen
<pb facs="tcp:24771:159"/>as wee vnderſtand that they were deliuered from thy mouth, ſaying.</p>
               <p>[<hi>Heare</hi> Iſrael] <hi>I am the Lord thy God, that brought thee out of the land of</hi> Aegypt, <hi>out of the houſe of bondage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1 Thou ſhalt haue no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods before mee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2 Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, or the likeneſſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, or in the water vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth. Thou ſhalt not bow downe to them, nor
<pb facs="tcp:24771:159"/>worſhip them, for I am the Lord thy God, a iealous God, that viſiteth the ſins of the fathers vppon the children, to the third and fourth generation of them that hate me, &amp; ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vnto thouſands, of them that loue me and keepe my commandements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3 Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine, for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſſe that taketh his name in vaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4 Remember that thou keepe holy the Sabaoth day, ſixe dayes ſhalt thou labor,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:160"/>and doe all that thou haſt to doe, but the ſeauenth day is the Sabaoth of the Lord: In it thou ſhalt do no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of thing, thou and thy ſonne, and thy daughter, and thy man-ſeruant, and thy maide-ſeruant, and the ſtranger that is within thy gates: for in ſixe dayes the Lord made heauen and earth, and the ſea, and all that therein is, and reſted the ſeauenth day, wherefore the Lord bleſſed the ſeuenth day, and hallowed it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5 Honour thy father &amp; mother, that thy dayes may
<pb facs="tcp:24771:160"/>be long in the land which the Lord thy God giueth thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6 Thou ſhalt do no mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7 Thou ſhalt not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adulterie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8 Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9 Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>10 Thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours houſe, thou ſhalt not couet thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours wife, nor his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruant, nor his maide-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, nor his oxe, nor his aſſe, nor any thing that is his.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:161"/>
               <p>And the ſumme of all theſe commandements is this: That wee loue thee O Lord, with al our hearts, and with all our mindes, and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours as our ſelues. Thy bleſſing therefore, O our GOD and Father, with the peace of our Lord Ieſus, and the comforte of the Holy-ghoſt, be thus giuen vnto vs by thy grace, and remaine with vs for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:161"/>
               <head>The three and twentieth Prayer, Before meate, among the Family.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>The eyes of all creatures looke vp vnto thee O Lord, thou giueſt them meate in due ſeaſon, thou openeſt thy hand, and filleſt with thy bleſsing euery liuing thing, &amp;c.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 145.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:162"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> euerlaſting GOD and Father, we beſeeche thee to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend thy bleſſing vppon vs thy poore children &amp; ſeruants, and vppon the foode, which it pleaſeth thee, of thy goodnes, to giue vnto vs for the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance of our life, that we may vſe the ſame ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly and with thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, as thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. But aboue all things, giue vs grace to
<pb facs="tcp:24771:162"/>deſire, and eſpecially to ſeeke the ſpirituall bread of thy word, wherewith our ſoules may be fed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally in the name, &amp; to the glory of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Sonne, and Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghoſt, one only and true God, who liueth and raigneth world without end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="prayer">
               <head>The foure and twenieth Prayer.
<pb facs="tcp:24771:163"/>After meales among the Family.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Whether wee eate or drinke, or whatſoeuer wee doe, we muſt doe all to the glory of God.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1. Cor. 10.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall God, our Father, we yeeld thee thanks, for that it hath pleaſed thee to nouriſh and feede vs, miniſtring vnto vs all that is needefull for this
<pb facs="tcp:24771:163"/>life, and making vs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy ſo many temporall benefites as thou doeſt largely poure vppon vs thy creatures: wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vouchſafe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue them the reſt of our dayes. But aboue al, wee praiſe thee for the ſpiritual foode, that by thy word thou giueſt to our ſoules, to the ende they may for euer liue in bliſſe, through Ieſus Chriſt our redeemer: to whome with the Father, and the Holi-ghoſt one
<pb facs="tcp:24771:164"/>onely and true God, be all honour and glory for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="prayer">
               <head>The fiue and twentieth Prayer. Euening Prayer for the Houſhold.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>It is a good thing to giue thanks vnto the Lord, and to ſing praiſes vnto thy name, O most high! to tell of thy trueth in the night ſeaſon. I will lay me downe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:164"/>in peace, and take my rest, for it is thou Lord onelie that makest mee dwell in ſafetie.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Pſal. 92. &amp; 4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord our god and Father, as thy people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> offered vnto thee their euening ſacrifice, ſo doe we offer vnto thee, the oblation of our humble and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heartes, that wee may glorifie thy name, and obtaine remiſſion of our ſinnes. We praiſe thee therefore and yeeld
<pb facs="tcp:24771:165"/>thee thanks for thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, namely for that it hath pleaſed thee to let vs paſſe this day, vnder thy protection and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, without the which wee might haue incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red manie miſeries and dangers. But, becauſe by our corruption and frailetie we haue diuerſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offended thee, in thought, worde, and deed, and that thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is vppon all thoſe to whom thou vouchſafeſt to be a Father, in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and
<pb facs="tcp:24771:165"/>that call vpon thy name, wee beſeech thee to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs our ſinnes, and to accept of his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in the merit of his death, in diſcharge of our debts: ſo that as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing is nowe hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from our eies by the night which thou giueſt vs for the reſt of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſo our offences may be buried out of thy ſight, in the ſepulchre of the ſame Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our ſoules may haue in him their ſpirituall reſt. Alas, we know that
<pb facs="tcp:24771:166"/>Sathan the Prince of darkeneſſe, lieth alwaies in waite to hurt vs, ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing principally to make a breach into our hearts when we ſtand leaſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our guarde: but (O Almightie God) in thy preſence alſo are the thouſands of Angels, to watch on thoſe whome thou haſt called to the inheritance of thy ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of which number wee doe beleeue our ſelues to be, through the mercie which it hath pleaſed thee to ſhewe vs.
<pb facs="tcp:24771:166"/>Giue vs grace therefore to be deliuered from the temptations of the diuel, from vncleaneneſſe, and troubleſome dreames, whereinto our infirmity doth leade vs, and alſo from all other dangers, to the ende our bodies receiuing, through thy bleſſing, a peaceable and quiet ſleep for their eaſe, our mindes may watch more freely vnto thee, (who art their reſt and their life) and in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of thy loue, that to morrowe wee may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:167"/>ſo much the readier, to glorifie &amp; ſerue thee, euery one in his vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thus running our race, in the path of thy elect, we may with ioy expect the deſired how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for our fleſh to reſt in the earth, that our ſoules may be lodged in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and at the laſt day be raiſed againe in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with al the Saints, to enioy the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our felicitie. Howbeit in the meane time, whilſt we comfort our ſelues in this hope,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:167"/>(O heauenlie Father) we doe recommend vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee the peace &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of thy church, the eſtate of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and all ſuch as be afflicted with ſicknes or anie other tribulation: beſeeching thee to giue to thy children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, whereof to take comfort, and alwayes to reioyce in thy goodnes. This is it that we doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in thy worde: Yea this is it, that wee doe craue of thee, in the name of our mediator
<pb facs="tcp:24771:168"/>Ieſus Chriſt, by that Prayer which hee hath taught vs. <hi>[Our father which art in heauen, &amp;c.]</hi> Thy bleſſing therefore O our God and Father, the peace of our Lorde Ieſus, with the comfort of the holy Ghoſt be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to vs by thy grace, and remaine with vs for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="prayer">
               <head>The ſixe and twentieth Prayer,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:168"/>Of him which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered much by ſickneſſe.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>When you ſhalbe ſicke, be not ſlowe to pray to God, and he will heale thee. Hee healeth thoſe that are bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in heart, and cureth their greefes. If they tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the gates of death, and crie vnto the Lord in their distreſſe, hee will deliuer them from their troubles.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Eccleſ. 18. Pſal. 147. &amp; 107.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:169"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, my GOD and father, now it is, that in theſe griefs and paines that oppreſſe me, I doe better then heretofore I haue, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and frailtie of my nature, and the iuſtice and goodneſſe of thy hand that viſiteth mee. The originall of all fleſh is in infection, his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall habitation is in duſt, continually toſſed
<pb facs="tcp:24771:169"/>to and fro with ſtormes: her end is a prey to the wormes, and all hir glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is buried with her in the earth. Yet is man ſo blinde, and depraued, that for a ſhorte time, wherein he enioyeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proſperity &amp; health, hee looſeth the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his fraile condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: he ſwells and ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from the principall end of his being, and ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth away into the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and vanities of the world. Thus might I ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times haue made ſhip
<pb facs="tcp:24771:170"/>wracke among theſe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable rockes, had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not thou my GOD, ſtretched forth thy rod of tribulation vpon mee in my moſt happy proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perities to preuent my ruine. It is, as euen to this day thou doeſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh me of thy diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, which maketh me to humble my ſelfe in thy ſight, and to feele my miſery, that with heart and voyce, I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that thou art iuſt (O ſoueraigne iudge) and good (O gentle Father)
<pb facs="tcp:24771:170"/>who wilt thus with one medecine, caſtize and cure the vlcer of my ſins: Come therefore thou vapor of the earth, thou ſhadow of life, thou cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible fleſh, ſith God for thy inſtruction and amendment giueth thee trauaile, put off thy ſelfe, and ſubmitte thee to his ſpirite, and thy ſpirite to the Father of ſpirits, and thy affections to his will. Thus with all thy ſtrength and minde, lift vppe thy ſelfe towards this Fatherly hand from
<pb facs="tcp:24771:171"/>whence the ſtripe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that grieueth thee, towards this arme of the almightie that hath caſt the ſtone that bruſeth thee: towards this great God, who being pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, doeth ſee and heare thee in thy ſufferings, who vnder his hand hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth both the diſeaſe &amp; the cure, the paine and the reſt, life and death, to make the one as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and heathfull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee as the other. Then will I ſay with a contrite heart, yet full of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:171"/>confidence: I haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt thee, O my God, I haue grieuouſly offended thee, I deſerue to be throughly chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and the diuells that I doe endure, are farre leſſe then my offences, which onely death and hell are able to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe. But thy grace and compaſſion greater then my ſinnes, are eternall vpon all thoſe whom thou haſt waſhed, fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and iuſtified in thy welbeloued Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, of which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:24771:172"/>I doe belieue I am, and that in him, and for his ſake thou wilt make me bleſſed: forgiue mee my debts in his name, and eaſe me of my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh wherein I remaine without ſtrength. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of my thoughts, in the bitternes of my hart, and with the words of <hi>Dauid,</hi> (O eternall God heare my prayer &amp; peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; let nothing hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my crie for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vnto thee, hide not thy face from me, bend
<pb facs="tcp:24771:172"/>downe thine eare vnto me in the day of my trouble, make haſte and deliuer me in the day that I call vpon thee, for my dayes are vaniſhed like ſmoake, and my bones are dried like chaf: my heart hath bin ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and withered like the graſſe, that I haue forgotten to eate my bread. O Lord, all my deſire is before thee, comfort the ſoule of thy ſeruant: ſhall any man tell of thy mercies in the ſepulchre, or thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:173"/>in the graue. Thus then, O mercifull God, bearing my ſelf in thy chaſtiſements, I will in all patience waite for the ſeaſonable ſuccour of thy hand, as being well aſſured, that while it is in comming, thou wilt not ſuffer thy ſpirit of conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to forſake mee in the middeſt of my tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, that my preſent heauineſſe ſhall be vnto mee the watch of ſome ioy at hand: and that at all aduentures, the laſt of my ſorrowefull dayes,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:173"/>ſhall be the firſt of my reſt in eternall life. And therefore I will againe ſay with the Apoſtle. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I am here, deale with me at thy pleaſure, and with thy ſeruant <hi>Iob,</hi> (Albeit God ſhould ſlay me, yet will I truſt in him, and reprooue my wayes in his preſence) &amp; with Saint <hi>Agustine</hi> (O Lord ſmite here, cutte here, burne here, ſo that thou dooſt pardon mee for euer,) <hi>Amen. Our Father which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:174"/>
               <head>The ſeauen and twenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Prayer. At the viſitation of the ſicke.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Is there any among you ſicke, let him call the elders of the Church, and let them pray for him, and annoint him with oyle, in the name of the Lord, and the prayer of faith ſhall ſaue the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the Lord ſhall raiſe him vp, and if hee haue committed any ſinnes, they ſhall bee forgiuen him.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Iames 5.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:174"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> LORD our GOD, who art all righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes &amp; goodneſſe, we knowe, that among thy corrections where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou wakeneſt vs to our duties, it pleaſeth thee many times to tame our fleſh with ſundry di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes: for thou doſt, by the pains that we ſuffer, aduertize vs of the cauſe of our euills, which is ſinne, and of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due to the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:175"/>namely death, whereof the infirmities of the body are the ordinary meanes: And alſo thou doeſt withall put vs in minde of the great day of thy Iudgement, which after death doeth enſue to life euerlaſting, full of glory and beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to the elect, and of reproach and torments to the rebrobate.</p>
               <p>But of theſe things, the fleſh, ſo long as it fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it ſelfe at eaſe, hath leaſt care to heare: Sith therefore it hath pleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:24771:175"/>thee, (O iuſt and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father) with thy rod to viſite this poore ſicke perſon here preſent, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting him for his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, as himſelfe doth with vs confeſſe, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee that in pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him for the loue of thy welbeloued Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, thou wilt make this chaſtizement to profit him to his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: ſo that he may with quiet obedience beare thy viſitation, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting himſelfe volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarie with all his heart to
<pb facs="tcp:24771:176"/>thy holy will, who ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt him, not as a ſeuere iudge, but as a moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Father, whereby he may learne to repoſe his whole truſt &amp; aſſurance in thy loue, &amp; as in him that art the author of his lif, &amp; canſt preſerue him, whither it be to abide be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low here in thy church, or that thou wilt gather him into thy kingdome of heauen. Thus Lord, on th'one ſide awakning in his ſoule by his ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, on th'other, the feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of humane miſeries,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:176"/>make him, with the eies of his faith, to behold the eternall bleſſings thou reſerueſt for him in thy Paradice, to liue happy for euer: ſo that he may with patience, eaſly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the bitterneſſe of that potion that thou haſt powred foorth vnto him, bending his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall deſire to enioy thy preſence in heauen. But thou knoweſt, O merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father, that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of thy children is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, but their fleſh is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes frayle, and full of
<pb facs="tcp:24771:177"/>great miſtruſt, eſpecially in the bitterneſſe of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
               <p>Aſſiſt, therefore this ſicke perſon with the plentie and ſtrength of the giftes of thy ſpirite, that he may ouercome all the enemies of his peace: and be thou his ſhield, againſt the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults &amp; terrors of death, eſpecially if his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence do trouble and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him for his inward and hidden ſins, which are open in thy ſight. Then let the holy Ghoſt
<pb facs="tcp:24771:177"/>(the perpetuall comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of all faithfull ſoules) vouchſafe to repreſent vnto him for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence the paſſion and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who hath himſelfe borne vpon the croſſe al our iniquities, that ſo he might abſolue and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge vs, before thy iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial throne (according to the infinite merite of his righteouſneſſe) and open the gate of thy Kingdome to all that ſhall beleeue and be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized in his name. Thus
<pb facs="tcp:24771:178"/>this poore patient being comforted in feeling, through a liuely &amp; ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt faith, the fruite and vertue of that earneſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of ſaluation that Chriſt hath left vs in his Church, namely remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinnes for his ſake: alſo that this hope which is neuer confounded, doth keepe his ſpirit qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, that he may call vpon thee, O Lord, and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy name, euen to his laſt gaſpe, neuer fearing the temptations of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, of death, or of hel,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:178"/>as beeing aſſured, that Chriſt hath ouercome them, &amp; ledde them in triumph, breaking their bonds, ſo that he may, in all Chriſtian confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, cry out with thy Apoſtle, O death, where is thy ſting? O hel, where is thy victory? In this manner, (O mercifull God) let this ſicke per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be, by our prayers, commended vnto thee: and vouchſafe, if it be thy pleaſure, to reſtore him to health, with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of thy graces, that
<pb facs="tcp:24771:179"/>he may yet amongeſt vs ſerue to thy glory. If not, but that thou haſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe appointed to bring him into thy reſt, thy will bee done, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted both by him and vs in al quiet obedience. Receiue him into thy heauenly <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> for hee hath his whole re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe vnto thee by one onelie mediatour Ieſus Chriſt, and all his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is in thy mercy. In ſteade of bodilie death graunt him the life of his ſoule amongeſt thy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:179"/>vntil that by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of all fleſh, in the great day of the LORD he may liue a whole man in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of thy glory. And to vs all heere pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent likewiſe graunt thy grace, that we may as we ought, beholde in this myrror, the ſhortneſſe and vncertainetie of our dayes, that hereafter we may not deſire anie thing ſo much as to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them carefully to thy honour and ſeruice. For all theſe thinges doe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:180"/>we pray vnto thee in the name of thy Sonne, in that Prayer which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath taught vs; <hi>Our father, which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="prayer">
               <head>The eight and twentieth Prayer, For him that feeleth his death at hand.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <p>Wee knowe, that if this earthly tabernacle be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,
<pb facs="tcp:24771:180"/>we haue a building giuen of God: that is, a houſe not made with hands but eternall in the heauens. The body is ſowen in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, it ſhall riſe againe in incorruption.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2. Cor. 5. 1. Cor. 15.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> GOD my God and FATHER, iuſtly was man, thy creature, when by ſinne he had turned from thee (who art the life) caſt headlong into the curſe
<pb facs="tcp:24771:181"/>both of temporall and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall death: for thy Maieſtie being infinitely offended, ought alſo in iuſtice to require a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment without end, which beginneth euen in this life in many miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and is perpetuated hell, whereto death is as it were the gate. O Lord! The cauſe of ſo lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a miſhap is in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: But in thee is pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and compaſſion, O mercifull Father, who after thy vnſpeakeable goodneſſe, makeſt the
<pb facs="tcp:24771:181"/>temporall death, which to all men is ineuitable, and to the reprobate an entry into hel, to change his qualitie concerning the Elect, beeing vnto them a ioyfull paſſage to that happineſſe which is in heauen: For Ieſus Chriſt thy eternall Son, to purchaſe vs this bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, did put on our fleſh, and therein healed the wound of ſinne by his righteouſneſſe: and by his oblation ſatisfied for our debt, triumphing by his reſurrection, ouer
<pb facs="tcp:24771:182"/>Death, Sathan, and Hel, for the ſaluation of thoſe to whome thou giueſt grace to belieue in his name. Now then, my God, ſith it hath pleaſed thee of thy great loue, thus to accompliſh the high myſterie of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, I beſeeche thee, grant mee to feele the fruite and efficacy thereof, through the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of thy ſpirit, euen to the laſt gaſpe of my life, that then I may render to thee my ſoule in peace. For I am bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed
<pb facs="tcp:24771:182"/>in the name of Chriſt, I belieue his holy goſpel, and am fed with his body and blood in the holy Church. True it is O Lord, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of my ſins, whereof my conſcience doeth accuſe mee doeth greatly trouble me; for the darkeneſſe of my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding hath kept me from knowing thee aright, and the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my heart from worſhipping thee in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and truth, according to thy word; I haue neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected
<pb facs="tcp:24771:183"/>this pretious trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, euen the voice of my Redeemer, and by my ſlackeneſſe, made the ſeede therof vnfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in my ſoule, many times preferring the loue of my ſelfe and the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the world, before the loue that I owe vnto thee (my Creator) and my neighbour for thy ſake. I haue not affected the croſſe of thy Sonne, that I might cheerefully carry mine after him, in renouncing all my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcences: neyther
<pb facs="tcp:24771:183"/>haue I applied thy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtizement to an vpright amendment of life: I haue beene weake in faith, ſlow in hope, cold in charitie, vnpatient in tribulation, and more ſtiffe in retaining other mens offences againſt mee, then ready to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them, what more ſhal I ſay, my God? Alſo many other ſins which I cannot expreſſe, which being euen at this day hidden from mee in my infirmities doe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme my ſoule, were
<pb facs="tcp:24771:184"/>it not for the repentance that thou graunteſt mee, and the truſt that I haue in thy mercy, through the righteouſneſſe of my Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, which it pleaſeth thee in thy Fatherly loue to make mine; I ſee nothing but matter of diſpaire. His ſacrifice giueth mee peace with thee: his blod cleanſeth me: his obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence abſolueth me: his woundes doe cure mee: In his torments my ſoule findeth her reſt: for of all theſe benefites doe I
<pb facs="tcp:24771:184"/>feele thy promiſe ſealed in my heart by thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which maketh me to crie vnto thee <hi>(Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther)</hi> and aſſureth me, that thou wilt of thy free mercy, in the name of thy Sonne, and for his ſake, giue mee remiſſion of my ſinnes, and eternal life, being illuminated; therefore, by this celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all light, I doe with the eies of my mind behold the ſhip that ſhall carry me ouer from earth to heauen, no farther off from the preſence of my
<pb facs="tcp:24771:185"/>Redeemer, then was that of his Diſciples, when they rowed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the tempeſt, to whom he ſaid (feare not, for it is I.) For in like maner commeth hee to meete mee, to ſay vnto me; Feare not, aſſure thy ſelfe, be conſtant; It is I, not the death which thou maiſt peraduenture feare, but hee that hath broken the ſting thereof, that hath led it in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, that hath broken the barres and bonds e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in hell; and who
<pb facs="tcp:24771:185"/>therefore doeth make thee to aſcend from the graue into the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of my glorie.</p>
               <p>Thus, my God, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened by thy grace with Chriſtian hope, which is not confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and couered vnder the buckler of Faith, which the darts of the diuell cannot wound, I am able with a ſtrong motion to pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e in peace from this priſon of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, with theſe laſt words of Ieſus Chriſt vpon the croſſe (Into
<pb facs="tcp:24771:186"/>thy hands, O LORD, I commend my ſpirit) and the ſame Chriſt ſaying vnto me, as to the poore theefe that was dying; Sonne reioyce, this day thou ſhalt be with me in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:24771:186" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
